<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.1" specific-use="sps-1.9">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
    <!-- OBRIGATORIO -->
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Revista BJLAS</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>

    <!-- OBRIGATORIO -->
    <article-meta>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>
      <bold>TOWARDS A SOUTH AMERICAN THEORY OF NUCLEAR DEVELOPMENT: </bold>
    </p>
    <p>
      <bold>NUCLEAR AUTONOMY AND REGIONAL SECURITY</bold>
    </p>
    <p>
      <italic>POR UMA TEORIA SUL-AMERICANA DE DESENVOLVIMENTO NUCLEAR: AUTONOMIA NUCLEAR E SEGURANÇA REGIONAL</italic>
    </p>
    <p>
      <italic>POR UNA TEORÍA SUDAMERICANA DE DESARROLLO NUCLEAR: AUTONOMÍA NUCLEAR Y SEGURIDAD REGIONAL</italic>
    </p>
    <p><italic>João Marcos Ferreira Pacheco</italic><fn id="fn0"><label>1</label><p> Ph.D. candidate in International Relations at Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP). E-mail: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="mailto:joao.m.pacheco@unesp.br">joao.m.pacheco@unesp.br</ext-link>. Corresponding Author.</p></fn> <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0009-0007-6640-5595"/></italic></p>
    <p>Universidade Estadual Paulista, Brazil</p>
    <p>
      <italic>João Paulo Nicolini Gabriel</italic>
      <fn id="fn1">
        <label>2</label>
        <p> Ph.D. in Political Science, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG). E-mail: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="mailto:joao.nicolini@uclouvain.be">joao.nicolini@uclouvain.be</ext-link></p>
      </fn>
      <italic>
        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4239-3522"/>
      </italic>
    </p>
    <p> Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais, Brazil</p>
    <p><bold>Abstract:</bold> This article aims to discuss the development of nuclear technology in South America through theoretical lenses that more accurately reflect the observable experiences of the region. The nuclear programs of Brazil and Argentina are contextualized within a theory of ‘nuclear autonomy,’ which is proposed here as an alternative to nuclear proliferation theories that are fundamentally focused on nuclear weapons and traditional international security approaches. It departs from a post-colonial and critical framework to challenge mainstream theories of nuclear proliferation and their applicability to the cases of Brazil and Argentina. The conclusions highlight the necessity of analyzing nuclear development in the region through lenses that prioritize discussions on economic development and autonomy rather than traditional security and proliferation of nuclear weapons. The widening of the concept of security as proposed by the School of Copenhagen and writings on autonomy by South American authors Helio Jaguaribe and Juan Carlos Puig serve as these lenses. Specialized literature on theories of nuclear proliferation, autonomy, and the history of the nuclear programs of Brazil and Argentina was used to develop this work.</p>
    <p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Nuclear Development; Nuclear Non-Proliferation; Autonomy; Brazil; Argentina. </p>
    <p><bold>Resumo:</bold> Este artigo tem como objetivo discutir o desenvolvimento da tecnologia nuclear na América do Sul por meio de lentes teóricas que reflitam com mais precisão as experiências observáveis da região. Os programas nucleares do Brasil e da Argentina são contextualizados dentro de uma teoria de "autonomia nuclear", proposta aqui como uma alternativa às teorias de proliferação nuclear que se concentram fundamentalmente em armas nucleares e abordagens tradicionais de segurança internacional. O artigo adota uma perspectiva pós-colonial e crítica para desafiar as teorias convencionais de proliferação nuclear e sua aplicabilidade aos casos do Brasil e da Argentina. As conclusões destacam a necessidade de analisar o desenvolvimento nuclear na região por meio de lentes que priorizem discussões sobre desenvolvimento econômico e autonomia, em vez de segurança tradicional e proliferação de armas nucleares. A ampliação do conceito de segurança, conforme proposta pela Escola de Copenhague, e os escritos sobre autonomia dos autores sul-americanos Helio Jaguaribe e Juan Carlos Puig servem como essas lentes analíticas. Esta pesquisa foi desenvolvida com base em literatura especializada sobre teorias de proliferação nuclear, autonomia e a história dos programas nucleares do Brasil e da Argentina.</p>
    <p><bold>Palavras-chave:</bold> Desenvolvimento Nuclear; Não-Proliferação Nuclear; Autonomia; Brasil; Argentina.  </p>
    <p><bold>Resumen:</bold> Este artículo tiene como objetivo discutir el desarrollo de la tecnología nuclear en América del Sur a través de lentes teóricas que reflejen con mayor precisión las experiencias observables de la región. Los programas nucleares de Brasil y Argentina se contextualizan dentro de una teoría de "autonomía nuclear", propuesta aquí como una alternativa a las teorías de proliferación nuclear que se centran fundamentalmente en las armas nucleares y en los enfoques tradicionales de seguridad internacional. El artículo adopta un marco poscolonial y crítico para cuestionar las teorías predominantes sobre la proliferación nuclear y su aplicabilidad a los casos de Brasil y Argentina. Las conclusiones subrayan la necesidad de analizar el desarrollo nuclear en la región a través de lentes que prioricen las discusiones sobre desarrollo económico y autonomía, en lugar de la seguridad tradicional y la proliferación de armas nucleares. La ampliación del concepto de seguridad, como la propone la Escuela de Copenhague, y los escritos sobre autonomía de los autores sudamericanos Helio Jaguaribe y Juan Carlos Puig, sirven como estas lentes analíticas. Este trabajo se desarrolló utilizando literatura especializada sobre teorías de proliferación nuclear, autonomía y la historia de los programas nucleares de Brasil y Argentina.</p>
    <p><bold>Palabras clave:</bold> Desarollo nuclear; No-proliferación nuclear; Autonomía; Brasil; Argentina. </p>
    <p> DOI:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.11606/issn.1676-6288.prolam.2025.227590">10.11606/issn.1676-6288.prolam.2025.227590</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.11606/issn.1676-6288.prolam.2025.227590">10.11606/issn.1676-6288.prolam.2025.227590</ext-link></p>
    <p>
      <italic>Received on: 31/07/2024</italic>
    </p>
    <p>
      <italic>Accepted on: 17/09/2025</italic>
    </p>
    <p>
      <italic>Published on: 22/12/2025</italic>
    </p>
    <p>
      <bold>1.Introduction</bold>
    </p>
    <p>This text aims to offer a theoretical framework with which to analyze the interest of South American countries in the use and mastery of nuclear technology, emphasizing its role in their strategies for scientific and technological development. In doing so, we argue that existing theories on the theme of nuclear proliferation privilege aspects of international security, nuclear deterrence, and international regimes, which do not offer accurate descriptions or analyses of the experiences in the region, particularly those of Brazil and Argentina. Instead of international security, military aggression, and regional conflicts, the control of such revolutionary technology was integral to their pursuit of economic and technological autonomy, a frequent topic in the domestic and foreign policies of countries in the region.</p>
    <p>Nuclear technology holds significant importance in International Relations (IR) debates, particularly in academic discussions within the Global North. This discourse was shaped by the Cold War, during which power dynamics and military concerns were paramount. Three main schools of thought dominate the field: neorealism, as represented by Kenneth Waltz's <italic>Theory of International Politics</italic> (1979), neoliberal institutionalism, exemplified by Robert Keohane and Joseph Nye's <italic>Power and Interdependence</italic> (1973) and Keohane's <italic>After Hegemony</italic> (1984), and constructivism, developed by works such as <italic>World of Our Making</italic> (2012, first published in 1989) by Nicholas Onuf and <italic>Anarchy is what States make of it </italic>(1992)by Alexander Wendt. This paper will summarize the contributions of these schools of thought to the study of nuclear technology development and argue that they are inaccurate or insufficient to understand the question in South America.</p>
    <p>Neorealists, such as Kenneth Waltz and John Mearsheimer, whose analyses are centered around the anarchic nature of the international system, argue that nuclear weapons contribute to international stability through nuclear deterrence, which is a strategy whereby a country’s gains in attacking another country with nuclear weapons are outweighed by the losses to the attacker caused by a nuclear response by the attacked country. According to such authors, this calculation results in a general refrain from using nuclear weapons, thus increasing stability and security (WALTZ, 1981; MEARSHEIMER, 1993). On the other hand, neoliberal institutionalists focus on international regimes, such as the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT) and the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA), which aim to prevent nuclear proliferation while promoting peaceful nuclear technology. Nuclear nonproliferation, thus, is seen as a result of international cooperation towards normative prohibition of the development of nuclear weapons and the promise of assistance in developing nuclear technology for peaceful uses (KEOHANE, 1984; NYE, 1981). </p>
    <p>Constructivists fundamentally argue that the political world is an intersubjective social construct. This construction is the result of the actions of agents and the influence of structures, which mutually influence each other. In this regard, constructivists value the concepts of constituted identities and norms in explaining issues in the international arena. While neorealists and neoliberal institutionalists create scenarios in which nuclear weapons proliferation is central to States’ securities, constructivists consider different objectives for acquiring nuclear weapons, which stem from the different <italic>meanings </italic>that states attribute to them, which in turn influence and are influenced by their identities<italic>. </italic>A key aspect of this theoretical framework is that, because these identities are particular to each state, one should be expected to analyze each case and create specific frameworks for them. This is a common movement for constructivist analyses, as constructivists generally reject the goal of developing universal criteria (HOPF, 1998). </p>
    <p>Stemming from constructivist thought, the School of Copenhagen comprises theoretical works which seek to expand the concept of security from a monolithic perspective centered around existential threats to states to that of an intersubjective construct with varying referents (BUZAN; WAEVER, 1998). This approach offers a useful starting point in order to analyze the particular cases of Brazil and Argentina for two reasons: firstly, a wider concept of security that departs from military issues and existential threats is particularly important to understand Brazil and Argentina’s nuclear ambitions. As will be demonstrated in this article, at no point in the history of their nuclear programs did either country perceive the other as posing an existential threat through the possession or use of nuclear weapons. Secondly, approaches to security that localize the referent to economic activities can include both countries’ efforts to develop nuclear industries and to supply their industrial development with nuclear energy. Therefore, the concepts of economic security and energy security are useful. However, we merely depart from a constructivist point of view in seeking to develop a theory that explains nuclear development in South America, arguing that economic and energy security are objectives of a larger, overarching objective: autonomy.</p>
    <p>Neorealists and neoliberalists have historically associated the development of nuclear technology with nuclear weapons and international security. We argue that such perspectives often overlook the aspirations of South American nations, specifically Brazil and Argentina. Constructivists, on the other hand, offer what is a starting point: the perspective that different meanings can be attributed to nuclear technology based on a country’s identities. We aim to give greater specificity to the study of Brazilian and Argentinian nuclear intentions by affirming that the meaning attributed to nuclear technology by the two countries is that of autonomy<italic>. </italic></p>
    <p>This paper makes evident that Brazil and Argentina historically pursued nuclear technology not intending to attain deterrence capabilities, but as a strategy for scientific and technological advancement, aiming for autonomy from global power structures. Autonomy here refers to the ability of states to develop independently, reducing reliance on external powers while enhancing their strategic and technological capabilities. Brazil and Argentina envisioned nuclear technology as a pathway to elevate their international status and achieve greater economic and technological independence. This pursuit was rooted in a broader strategy to break free from dependency on more developed nations and assert their sovereignty. The mastery of nuclear technology symbolized progress and the capacity to engage in high-tech industries, which were seen as crucial for national development. By focusing on the peaceful uses of nuclear technology, these South American states aimed to harness its potential for energy production, medical applications, and scientific research. This approach aligns with their broader developmental goals and the quest for a diversified and robust economy. </p>
    <p>In this context, it is essential to challenge the notion that the development of nuclear technology is inevitably linked to nuclear weapons proliferation. South American countries have demonstrated that it is possible to pursue nuclear technology for developmental purposes without escalating regional tensions or provoking arms races. This perspective is often overlooked in mainstream IR theories, which tend to emphasize the security dilemmas associated with nuclear proliferation. The chronological and historical timeframe of analysis is the entirety of Argentina and Brazil’s nuclear programs, ranging from the early 1950s to the present day. We argue that, although both countries experienced significantly different types of government, having been under military dictatorships from 1964 to 1984 in Brazil and from 1955 to 1958, 1966 to 1973, and 1976 to 1983 in Argentina, the relationship between the two was characterized as a scientific competition for technological superiority in the region during military governments and integration for trust-building and cooperation during civilian governments. There was never a context of a security dilemma or an arms race. </p>
    <p>Departing from decolonial and critical theories, we question the biases inherent in mainstream IR theories and highlight the unique paths to autonomy taken by South American nations. For postcolonial thought, state policies not only create hierarchies in the international system, but the production of scientific knowledge also shapes how states and societies interact (LAFFEY; WELDES, 2008). Knowledge produced in specific contexts often presents local perspectives as universal truths, favoring those in power. This critique highlights that all theories reflect their geographical and historical origins, showing that knowledge is never neutral or objective but tied to places of power. For instance, International Relations theories often rely on Eurocentric narratives, prioritizing the views of dominant states in the global system (LAFFEY; WELDES, 2008, p. 556).</p>
    <p>Andrew Linklater (1996) reinforces this critique by arguing that knowledge is shaped by pre-existing social interests and is not a neutral reflection of reality (p. 297). He challenges the assumption that reality is objective and immutable, instead suggesting that knowledge can maintain hierarchical structures that subjugate weaker actors by presenting these structures as natural and unchangeable (p. 279). For example, terms like "human nature" or "the course of history" often obscure human agency and the potential for transformation. In neorealism, the international system’s anarchy forces states to seek survival and power. However, this view can be critiqued: war and peace are not inevitable outcomes of anarchy but depend on the ambitions of great powers, their foreign policies, and the effectiveness of norms constraining their behavior (LINKLATER, 1996, p. 283). </p>
    <p>Conflict and competition are not fixed features of the system but are shaped by human agency and decisions. Postcolonial and critical theories encourage deconstructing Eurocentric knowledge to build perspectives closer to South American contexts. For instance, while the nuclear non-proliferation regime often reflects the interests of great powers, this article argues for a focus on the concerns of developing countries. Autonomy is a key concept for South America, shaping its approach to nuclear development and policy. </p>
    <p> The concept of autonomy and its application as a theoretical framework allow us to understand the diverse motivations behind nuclear development and recognize the agency of South American countries in shaping their destinies. The pursuit of nuclear technology in South America represents a form of resistance against the dominant paradigms imposed by the Global North and an assertion of their right to self-determined development.</p>
    <p>This article proposes the concept of “nuclear autonomy” as a core principle from which stem the political and technological, domestic and international aspirations of South American countries, especially Brazil and Argentina<fn id="fn2"><label>3</label><p> The choice of Brazil and Argentina is due to the fact that both countries are the only ones in South America to have been able to develop robust nuclear programs. Peru, Chile, Venezuela and Colombia have very incipient nuclear programs, having purchased a small number of research nuclear reactors to operate for research purposes. The conditions under which countries are able to pursue nuclear autonomy are discussed throughout the text. </p></fn>. Put simply, nuclear autonomy is the capacity to master, produce, and apply nuclear technology and the nuclear fuel cycle on both small and large scales, without relying on foreign countries or being subject to constraints imposed by them. We discuss autonomy as an overarching aspect of South American policymaking through the works of authors Helio Jaguaribe, such as “<italic>Autonomía periférica y hegemonía céntrica</italic>” (1979), and Juan Carlos Puig, such as “<italic>Integración y autonomía de América Latina en las postrimerías del siglo XX</italic>” (1986) and the specificities of nuclear autonomy through observance of the histories of Brazil and Argentina’s nuclear programs. </p>
    <p>
      <bold>2.Research Design </bold>
    </p>
    <p>This article employs a qualitative approach, using the case studies of Brazil and Argentina to apply and evaluate the proposed theoretical framework of "nuclear autonomy." By focusing on these two countries, the study conducts a deductive analysis to test the hypothesis that their nuclear programs are better understood through a lens prioritizing autonomy and economic development rather than traditional security-driven narratives.</p>
    <p>The research mobilizes existing bibliographic sources and specialized literature, including writings on theories of nuclear proliferation, works by authors Barry Buzan, Ole Wæver and Jaap de Wilde that comprise the School of Copenhagen,  the concept of autonomy as discussed by South American scholars such as Helio Jaguaribe and Juan Carlos Puig, and the historical development of the nuclear programs in Brazil and Argentina. These materials are analyzed to construct an alternative framework that challenges mainstream theories and offers a more regionally relevant perspective.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>3.International security as a concept </bold>
    </p>
    <p>In order to create an alternative to mainstream perspectives on nuclear development, which have privileged aspects of international and military security, it is necessary to define such perspectives. We argue that discussions in the field of international relations on the development of nuclear technology have been fundamentally derivative of a concept of security that is concerned with analyzing existential threats to a national state, its government, its territory, and its population. This concept is what Buzan, Waever and Wilde (1998, p. 21) define as “the traditional military-political understanding of security”. In the field of IR, three main discussions arose from the existential threat posed by the use of nuclear weapons. A first topic is the set of concepts that explain military strategies and how the possession and use of nuclear weapons serve them; a second discussion has at its center explanatory models that seek to explain why countries acquire nuclear weapons. A third debate is concerned with the spread of nuclear technology and how it relates to the proliferation of nuclear weapons.  </p>
    <p>In the second half of the 20th century, a period marked by bipolarity and an arms race between the United States and the Soviet Union, strategists and theorists developed the concept of “nuclear deterrence” to analyze nuclear weapons and their effects on interstate conflicts and relations, especially between the two superpowers. The book “Deterrence and Defense” (1961), by Glenn H. Snyder, seeks to define and explain the concepts of defense and deterrence, the relations between them, and the role that nuclear weapons have in achieving such strategies. In his book, Snyder dedicates the second chapter to discussing the national defense of the United States against Soviet nuclear strikes, presenting concepts regarding the use and employment of nuclear weapons such as “first-strike”, “punitive capability”, “counterforce capability”, amongst others (SNYDER, 1961). Likewise, Kenneth Waltz (1981) associates the capability of a “second-strike” nuclear attack as the key to deterrence strategies of these superpowers. These works have since been followed by an extensive literature that aims to discuss the pursuit, possession and use of nuclear weapons, ranging from optimistic visions, which point to the decrease of risks of conflict and consequent increase in state security, to pessimistic visions, which point to the possibility of preventive war or escalatory risks (BELL; MILLER, 2016).</p>
    <p>Along with studies on the use of nuclear weapons by countries that possess them, the literature on nuclear weapons and international security contains a myriad of studies and explanatory models that focus on the question of nuclear weapons proliferation, that is, the possibility that a growing number of countries would pursue such weapons to acquire nuclear deterrence capabilities. Most exemplary of this debate is the work by Scott D. Sagan “Why Do States Build Nuclear Weapons?: Three Models in Search of a Bomb” (1996), in which the author offers models based on international security, domestic politics and identity-building aspects to explain why countries choose to develop nuclear weapons. </p>
    <p>Finally, scholars have analyzed the relation between the development of nuclear technology and the acquisition of nuclear weapons. José Goldemberg (2009) argues that "the widespread circulation of fissile materials, particularly in politically unstable countries, increases the likelihood that some of this material could fall into the hands of terrorist groups" (GOLDEMBERG, 2009, p. 78). Concerns that developing countries could seek mastery of nuclear technology to develop nuclear weapons programs are heightened, especially in highly securitized contexts such as the Iranian nuclear program (DENZA, 2005; MONTEIRO; DEBS, 2014; MILLER; SAGAN, 2009). Goldemberg (2009) concludes that a nuclear renaissance—greater interest from an increasing number of countries in mastering the nuclear fuel cycle to avoid dependence and even participation in international markets for nuclear materials and fuels—would weaken the current oligopoly of major nuclear powers. This, according to the author, has the potential to weaken the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (GOLDEMBERG, 2009, p. 79). This discourse, based on international security terms, predicts greater risks to countries' security due to an increase in the number of nuclear-capable states. Such conclusions evidently correlate the development of nuclear technology with the proliferation of nuclear weapons, as if the latter outcome were an intrinsic result of the former. We dispute this perspective by showing that Brazil and Argentina’s pursuit has not led to security threats in the region.</p>
    <p>Overall, the discussion on nuclear technology has been highly securitized. Analyzing the literature on the proliferation of nuclear weapons, Debs and Monteiro (2017) identify three phases: The first phase is strongly characterized by security, explaining that states seek nuclear weapons when there are threats to their security and survival. The second phase brings explanations related to nationalist and political perceptions, which would lead states to pursue nuclear weapons for projection in the international system. The third phase includes the issue of the supply of nuclear materials and technologies as a cause for nuclear proliferation (DEBS; MONTEIRO, 2017). The focus of this literature, therefore, associates the pursuit of nuclear technology intending to acquire nuclear weapons. </p>
    <p>From the traditional perspectives on international security and starting in the 1980s, much work has been done in theoretical endeavors which seek to expand and widen the concept of security beyond that of interstate relations and military strategies (BUZAN; HANSEN, 2009; BUZAN; WAEVER; WILDE, 1998). What has come to be known as the School of Copenhagen is the group of works that stem from the perspectives on security put forward by authors Barry Buzan, Ole Waever and Jaap de Wilde in their book “Security: A New Framework for Analysis” (1998).  The core of the School of Copenhagen is the concept of “securitization,” which is “the discursive process through which an intersubjective understanding is constructed within a political community to treat something as an existential threat to a valued referent object, and to enable a call for urgent and exceptional measures to deal with the threat” (BUZAN; WAEVER, 2003, p. 491). </p>
    <p>We argue that the pursuit of nuclear technology by Brazil and Argentina is not accurately explained by traditional concepts of security, which associate such pursuit with the objective of acquiring nuclear weapons and deterrence capabilities, which in turn are considerably securitized matters. As explained in this section, much attention has been given to the matter of nuclear weapons and their role in strategic and defense studies, nuclear proliferation, and the reasons for acquiring nuclear weapons. However, a qualitative and historical analysis of the nuclear programs of Brazil and Argentina empirically show that these traditional-security aspects are insufficient to explain these countries aspirations, as neither country poses an existential threat to each other, other countries or the region through the pursuit of nuclear weapons, their possession or threat of use. For this reason, we claim that a widened concept of security, as discussed by the School of Copenhagen, can offer a more accurate analysis. Specifically for the matter at hand, we argue that the concepts of economic security and energy security are useful.</p>
    <p>Economic security is the assurance of the supply of resources that are essential to a country’s economic activities<fn id="fn3"><label>4</label><p> Economic security as a concept has had different meanings depending on different perspectives. It has been used to refer to aspects of trade and commerce that have direct consequences in defense, such as weapons trade and military technology. In this sense, it is related to the concept of geo-economics. See Cable (1995).  </p></fn>. Cable (1995) describes two problems that could arise in the external supply of such resources. The first is related to the availability of supply, which can be interrupted by contexts of war, conflicts, sanctions or natural disasters. The second is related to the concentration of supply and creation of monopolies in materials and technologies which could make the terms of trade precarious to the importer.  In this sense, ideas of self-reliance become important in orienting policy makers in order to create economic conditions to realize activities that are more or less immune to interference or disruption from external sources<fn id="fn4"><label>5</label><p> The relationship between economic interdependence and economic security is perceived differently by developed or developing countries. See Kahler (2004) and Nesadurai (2004).</p></fn>. </p>
    <p>Energy security is closely related to economic security insofar as it refers to the supply of energy and the production of energy as a national economic activity. A secure energy supply means that energy sources must be affordable, sufficient, continuous, and consistent in order to meet a country’s requirements. While the concept has been a preoccupation of policy makers since the early 20<sup>th</sup> century, discussions on energy security have received increased attention since the 1970s due to the oil crises (YERGIN, 2006)<fn id="fn5"><label>6</label><p> In the second half of the 20<sup>th</sup> century, the focus was primarily on the supply of oil, since that was the most common energy source in highly industrialized countries. In this sense, energy security meant the reliable supply of oil from producers, meaning affordable prices, which in turn could be severely compromised by oil price shocks caused by contexts of war, conflicts and other crises in producing countries. This prompted discussions on the necessity of diversifying the sources of oil exports (YERGIN, 2006).</p></fn>.  </p>
    <p>By the end of the 20<sup>th</sup> century and the beginning of the 21<sup>st</sup> century, economic interdependence, the industrialization of an expanding number of countries, the growth in international demand for energy, and an increase in preoccupations with environmental issues and the use of fossil fuels have broadened the concept that has included the increase in the net supply of energy, meaning that overreliance on oil and fossil fuels could be a problem in achieving a secured supply of energy. In this context, alternative sources such as solar, wind, hydro, geothermal and nuclear power have steadily become objectives of energy supply policies in a myriad of countries (KLARE, 2013).</p>
    <p>These sources of energy, of course, face challenges related to interdependence, access to technology and the international supply of essential minerals and fuel. It is in this perspective that the concepts of economic security and energy security intertwine and are useful. In the cases of Brazil and Argentina, nuclear energy is considerably a matter of economic and energy security as it 1) still depends on the external supply of technology, which is a very securitized aspect of international trade due to its characteristic of dual use<fn id="fn6"><label>7</label><p> The Nuclear Suppliers Group is an international conglomerate of countries with advanced nuclear technology that sets parameters and rules for the export of sensitive technologies and materials in order to guarantee that receiving countries do not divert such technologies and materials to nuclear weapons programs. See Burr (2014) and Viski (2012).</p></fn>, 2) is considered a viable source in diversifying both countries’ energy matrices. Therefore, we argue that the pursuit of nuclear technology by Brazil and Argentina can be partially explained as a quest for the ability to guarantee a diversified energy source net through the availability of nuclear energy production and an assured technological development of the nuclear sector through a decrease in dependence on foreign technology. These two aspects, however, are embedded within a broader and less tangible objective that drives domestic and foreign policy in Brazil and Argentina, that of autonomy. </p>
    <p>
      <bold>4.The concept of Autonomy in South America</bold>
    </p>
    <p>To mobilize the concept of autonomy, it is essential to define it. Vigevani and Cepaluni (2011) highlight the distinction between mainstream International Relations (IR) theories, centered on Europe and the United States, and South American perspectives. In mainstream IR, autonomy is a normative and legal concept, where states are autonomous and sovereign entities within an anarchic order. In South America, however, autonomy has historically been framed in political and economic terms, describing a foreign policy free from the constraints of powerful countries (VIGEVANI; CEPALUNI, 2011, p. 27).</p>
    <p>Focusing on South American scholarship, Vigevani and Cepaluni (2011) define autonomy as the "ability of the State to implement decisions based on its own objectives, without external interference or restriction, through its ability to control processes or events produced beyond its borders" (p. 30). Similarly, Simonoff and Lorenzini (2019) describe it as "the ability to make one's own decisions based on each country's interests, with freedom of judgment and according to their perspectives" (p. 99). Thus, a policy free from external interference is generally characterized as “autonomous” in South American countries. </p>
    <p>Hélio Jaguaribe and Juan Carlos Puig are key figures in what Briceño, Ruiz and Simonoff (2017) call the School of Autonomy. By analyzing South American international politics through the lens of political and economic autonomy, Jaguaribe and Puig developed a distinct South American theory of international relations. This perspective will be used here to discuss nuclear development in the region, emphasizing that South American interests often differ from the power and security concerns predominant in Global North theories. In "<italic>Autonomía periférica y hegemonía céntrica</italic>" (1979), Jaguaribe categorizes the international system into central countries, which enjoy general primacy; dependent countries; and autonomous countries, which act according to their own interests. He further classifies autonomous countries by their type of autonomy: general autonomy (e.g., the United States), regional autonomy (e.g., Brazil in Latin America), and sectoral autonomy (e.g., Saudi Arabia in oil trade).</p>
    <p>Jaguaribe also identifies two enabling conditions for autonomy<fn id="fn7"><label>8</label><p> Jaguaribe describes two different orders of conditions for autonomy: enabling conditions, which are <italic>national viability</italic> and <italic>international permissiveness</italic>; and a second order which is related to different models of organization of a system which creates different types of relations between the center and the periphery. These are the <italic>ethnocentric</italic> model, the <italic>centrist omnicomprehensive culturalist</italic> model and the <italic>universalizing and equalizing ecumenist</italic> model (See JAGUARIBE, 1979). The first order of condition is instrumentalized in this article to develop the concept of nuclear autonomy as a sectoral autonomy. The second order is of a much broader scope and is related to discussions of general autonomy, which is not the aim of this article. </p></fn>: national viability and international permissiveness. <italic>National viability</italic> is the ability of a country to have a critical minimum of human and natural resources necessary for carrying out its project, including the capacity for international trade (JAGUARIBE, 1979, p. 96). It can also be defined as the set of internal conditions that dependent countries must have in order for the national autonomist elite to begin the gradual process of overcoming dependency (SIMONOFF, LORENZINI, 2019, p. 98). International permissiveness is the ability of a country to neutralize coercion coming from third-party countries (JAGUARIBE, 1979, p. 97). That is, the assortment of conditions of possibility for a state or a group of states to implement an autonomist strategy, taking into account the state of the situation or the degree of constraints imposed by the international system, specifically the states that make up the power oligopoly (SIMONOFF, LORENZINI, 2019, p. 99). </p>
    <p>Juan Carlos Puig discusses integration, defined as "conducts that aim to allow the social groups in question to renounce individual action in certain matters to do so jointly and with a sense of permanence" (PUIG, 1986, p. 41). Integration is crucial for achieving autonomy, as it enables collective development. Puig differentiates between interdependent integration, characterized by dependency between the center and periphery, and solidarity integration, based on shared status or values. In the School of Autonomy, integration is seen as a means to pursue autonomy, combining mutual capacities to enhance development and the autonomist process. Thus, integration is both an instrument and a value driving the pursuit of autonomy (PUIG, 1986, p. 44).</p>
    <p>Stemming directly from this theoretical framework, we propose the concept of nuclear autonomy based on these understandings about the political and economic realities of South America. The first thing to understand is that the present discussion is an exact application of Jaguaribe’s “sectoral autonomy”.  We argue that nuclear autonomy is not a result of general autonomy, but an economic activity or sector in which autonomy can be sought. This, of course, <italic>may</italic> lead to further levels of autonomy which could lead a state to general autonomy. We do not suggest that nuclear autonomy is necessarily a step to general autonomy in a teleological manner. In fact, Jaguaribe’s description of <italic>general autonomy</italic> is characterized by territorial impregnability, which is guaranteed by nuclear deterrence capacity (JAGUARIBE, 1979, p. 92). Hence, it is important that we frame the concept of nuclear autonomy as <italic>sectoral autonomy,</italic> lest the discussion rails back to focusing on traditional security.</p>
    <p>Historically, nuclear energy has been regarded as a "passport to the First World" (GOLDEMBERG, 2009, p. 71). The status of a country possessing nuclear technology was seen as equivalent to the status of a great power. The issue of nuclear technology for developing countries was present in President Dwight Eisenhower's Atoms for Peace speech in 1953 and was also raised in the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty: its article IV determines that nuclear technology will be used for development purposes for underdeveloped countries. Despite this, there are no studies to date that prove a direct causal relationship between nuclear energy and economic development. The relationships found are diverse and inconclusive in this regard (WOLDE-RUFAEL; MENYAH, 2009, p. 551). Therefore, this article is not an assessment of the capacity of nuclear autonomy to lead a country into general autonomy, but, rather, an analysis that treats nuclear autonomy as an end in itself.</p>
    <p>Having that explained, the conceptualization is as follows: nuclear autonomy refers to the capacity of a country to develop and construct scientific, technical and technological knowledge related to atomic nature; to apply this knowledge in domestically developing, building and manufacturing projects, machineries and devices for purposes of electric energy generation, medicine, propulsion and other peaceful uses of nuclear reactions that such country deem necessary to its national objectives of development; to master and operate all steps of the nuclear fuel cycle to supply such uses; and to engage in bilateral and multilateral cooperations to share and develop nuclear technology for peaceful uses with other countries without interference or constraints imposed in any manner by foreign countries and international institutions.</p>
    <p>Applying the conceptual tools offered by Jaguaribe and Puig, we propose the following framework:</p>
    <p>National viability as the critical amount of natural and human resources for achieving nuclear autonomy includes a large amount of uranium-rich minerals in a country’s territory in order to fuel all technical activities originating from nuclear reactions, as well as a sufficiently developed metallurgical industry capable of supplying all physical constructions of nuclear facilities and equipment. Human resources include a large national body of scientists, technicians,, and engineers highly capable of realizing all projects on a laboratorial and industrial scale and developing or replicating nuclear technology. </p>
    <p>International permissiveness for achieving nuclear autonomy is related to the lack of restrictions imposed by great powers or established international institutions on national activities or international relations. Nuclear-weapon States have evidently interfered with countries seeking to develop nuclear technology, ranging from diplomatic boycotts in bilateral deals of technology transfer to economic sanctions. The Nuclear Suppliers Group has put forth a series of norms and rules that limit the trade of sensitive technology (VISKI, 2012), and the International Atomic Energy Agency has the responsibility of informing the Security Council of the UN of non-compliance cases, which can be met with sanctions. According to the present theory of nuclear autonomy, a country seeking nuclear autonomy is very likely to try to resist or neutralize such interference through diversification of partners or trust-building mechanisms and policies.</p>
    <p>Integration for achieving nuclear autonomy refers to the combination of capacities in order to develop nuclear technology and/or face international interference and constraints through coordinated action. This can be, for instance, scientific cooperation to share knowledge, materials, and personnel in order to facilitate achieving technical and scientific mastery of nuclear technology. It can also mean coordination of policies in order to resist international pressures or to gain the trust of other countries and institutions by offering collective assurance of peaceful relations and therefore peaceful uses of nuclear technology. </p>
    <p>Having laid out this theoretical framework, we move to analyzing Argentina and Brazil’s nuclear histories empirically:</p>
    <p>
      <bold>5.Argentina</bold>
    </p>
    <p>Argentina’s nuclear program began in the 1950s. It was marked by considerable efforts in the country’s scientific community to develop technical knowledge and acquire materials in order to foster research and capacitatenational technicians, engineers and scientists. The National Atomic Energy Commission (CNEA) was established in 1950 to coordinate and promote nuclear research, oversee the exploration, production, and commercialization of nuclear materials, and propose measures for nuclear energy applications in various economic sectors (SÁBATO, 1973). The establishment of research centers such as the Ezeiza Atomic Center, the Bariloche Atomic Center and the Balseiro Institute in the 1950s through the 1960s marked Argentina’s objective of mastering nuclear technology and its applications. Through a partnership with Siemens, a German company, Argentina inaugurated Latin America's first nuclear power plant, Atucha I, in 1974. Of particular importance is the choice for a reactor that uses natural uranium as fuel and heavy water as the reactor moderator. This choice represented the objective of guaranteeing that Argentina would be able to fuel the power plant with its own natural uranium without the need for enrichment, a technology that was not mastered at the time. This, consequently, meant that Argentina would not depend on the external supply of nuclear fuel (HURTADO, 2014). </p>
    <p>Despite needing to hire foreign expertise due to limited domestic capabilities, efforts were made to involve CNEA and Argentine private companies in nuclear projects (ORNSTEIN, 2010). Atucha I and Atucha II nuclear plants utilize German technology, while the Embalse nuclear plant uses Canadian technology, all using natural uranium as fuel and heavy water as a moderator (REDICK, 1995). Research reactors, however, were designed and built in Argentina, sometimes adapting foreign designs to local needs (ORNSTEIN, 2010). In 2007, the creation of the Argentinian Ministry of Science, Technology, and Innovation made science and technology a state policy, leading to initiatives like repatriating scientists and creating funding programs for applied science (VERA; COLOMBO, 2011; VERA, 2013). The pursuit of industrial-scale enrichment aimed to reduce dependence on the limited market for enriched uranium. As part of the Argentine Nuclear Activity Reactivation Plan launched in 2006, CNEA aimed to achieve complete control over the nuclear fuel cycle (COLOMBO; GUGLIELMINOTTI; VERA, 2017).</p>
    <p>In 2015, President Cristina Kirchner announced the operation of the uranium enrichment plant at the Pilcaniyeu Technological Complex, using the gas diffusion method. By 2019, plans for a laser enrichment plant were underway (SANTORO, 2015; ALONSO, 2019). The Argentine Multipurpose Reactor RA-10, approved in 2010, was the first fully designed and built research reactor in Argentina and Latin America, developed by INVAP, an Argentinian state company. It aims to produce radioisotopes and test new fuel elements, with a design contract involving INVAP, CNEN (Brazil), and CNEA (BLAUMANN et al., 2012). The Argentine Modular Elements Center (CAREM) is a prototype low-power nuclear reactor entirely developed in Argentina, a partnership between INVAP and CNEA, which also developed the reactor's fuel (ALBORNOZ, 2018). In 2019, the Argentinian Government published a document called “<italic>Escenarios Energéticos 2030</italic>”, whose aim was to divulge studies on energetic policies in the country until the year 2030. The document cites the potential of nuclear energy to increase the country’s energy net supply and to decrease its dependency on fossil fuel sources (ARGENTINA, 2019). </p>
    <p> Argentina has a significant degree of national viability for nuclear autonomy. In terms of natural resources, CNEA has informed that government and private prospections have identified 31.000 tons of natural uranium in Argentinian territory (ARGENTINA, 2016). In terms of human resources, it is evident that the history of Argentina’s nuclear program is fundamentally a history of how the government, influenced by the scientific sector in varying degrees, sought to create domestic institutions to foster research and education on critical subjects and areas to have a highly capable sector of nuclear scientists, technicians and engineers. As a result, Argentina has mastered enrichment technology and, therefore, the nuclear fuel cycle. This makes it one of the few countries witch such capacity. </p>
    <p>In terms of international permissiveness, Argentina has come a historical trajectory from refusing to sign the NPT and being targeted as a latent proliferator country to participating in numerous international institutions pertaining to nuclear safety and non-proliferation. In the aftermath of India’s successful nuclear weapon test in 1974, Argentina was compared to the South-Asian country as a latent proliferator and suffered consequences as further restrictions and requirements were imposed by Canada in their nuclear cooperation (MENDOZA, 2005). From the 2000s, Argentina's nuclear diplomacy aimed to enhance the country's credibility as a supplier and exporter of nuclear materials. For Argentine governments, this was pursued through active participation in numerous treaties and agreements related to nuclear issues (COLOMBO; GUGLIELMINOTTI; VERA, 2017). Additionally, mention is made of the numerous bilateral agreements Argentina has with various countries for nuclear cooperation, with particular emphasis on the sale of the OPAL research reactor to Australia. The degree of international permissiveness, thus, has increased as Argentina has gained international credibility of its peaceful development of advanced nuclear technology and the resulting lack of interference of central powers or international institutions in its commercial activities. In fact, Argentinian diplomat Rafael Grossi was appointed Secretary-General of the International Atomic Energy Agency, which exemplifies Argentina’s high credentials as trusted by the international community.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>6.Brazil</bold>
    </p>
    <p>Brazil's nuclear history began in the 1940s with agreements for its strategic minerals (monazite) with the United States. At the time, Brazil traded its monazite for American wheat (OLIVEIRA, 1991, p. 73). In the 1950s, influenced by Navy Admiral Álvaro Alberto, a policy was instituted whereby Brazil's export of natural uranium to the United States should be conditional on U.S. technological assistance in Brazil’s bourgeoning nuclear development. This marked the start of Brazil’s nuclear autonomy ambitions. During the dictatorship, President Costa e Silva stated in a speech at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs that nuclear energy was the most powerful resource that should be made available to developing countries in order to reduce the gap between them and industrialized nations (ANDRADE, 2006, p. 130). However, a series of political disagreements between the government, military, and scientific sectors led Brazil's first nuclear reactor to be purchased from Westinghouse in 1972, a reactor that used light-water technology and enriched uranium. This led to maintaining a relationship of dependency on US enriched uranium (NICOLINI GABRIEL, 2023; LUGONES; VERA, 2023; PATTI, 2021). </p>
    <p>Following tightened US controls in 1974 after India’s nuclear test, which resulted in a precarious supply of American nuclear fuel to Brazil’s reactors, Brazil sought to diversify its partnerships, acquiring German technology for its second reactor in 1975. When the Brazilian-Germany deal suffered from protests and boycotts by the United States, Brazil launched the domestic Parallel Program in 1979 to develop uranium enrichment technology domestically (DUNLAP, 2017; REDICK, 1995). The Parallel Program was a series of technical and technological developments by the branches of the armed forces in order to develop indigenous uranium enrichment technology. The result of this endeavor was The Navy's significant achievement of developing ultracentrifuge technology for uranium enrichment in 1982, primarily intended to fuel nuclear-powered submarines, a project that began during this period (REDICK, 1995; WROBEL, 2017). </p>
    <p>In 2000, the Brazilian Nuclear Industries (INB) and the Brazilian Navy began constructing an industrial-scale uranium enrichment facility, inaugurated in Resende in 2006, to ensure a stable nuclear fuel supply for the Angra I and Angra II plants (CABRERA-PALMER; ROTHWELL, 2008; ROSA, 2007). The 2008 National Defense Strategy positioned nuclear development as vital for Brazil's economic and defense strategies, aiming for mastery of the nuclear fuel cycle, energy diversification, and establishing Brazil as a major nuclear fuel exporter (ARGÜELLO, 2011). This aligns with Brazil's neo-developmentalism framework, prioritizing infrastructure investment (HERZ; DAWOOD; LAGE, 2017). </p>
    <p>Brazil’s quest for a nuclear-powered submarine should be understood within the same development-oriented and autonomy-seeking framework. It started in the end of the 1970s and has been an objective of the Brazilian Navy and the Brazilian government with varying degrees of priority depending on the political and economic moment and administration. While the issue of a Non-Nuclear Weapons State pursuing nuclear technology for propulsion uses holds particular significance within discussions of proliferation (See SPEKTOR, 2018), official discourse from Brazil’s Navy has pointed to necessities concerning Brazil’s strategic interest in its coastal area and technological modernization. Admiral José Alberto Accioly Fragelli stated that a nuclear-propelled submarine would elevate Brazil's military and strategic stature (MARTINS FILHO, 2011). In 2008, the PROSUB (Submarine Development Program) was launched, part of a larger bilateral partnership with France. The Lula administration's broader vision for international integration found support among the military, with the construction of a nuclear-propelled submarine seen as essential for securing a UNSC seat, a very long-lasting objective present in Brazil’s international insertion (MARTINS FILHO, 2011; JESUS, 2012; DIEHL; FUJII, 2009). </p>
    <p>As a prerequisite for autonomy, Brazil has sought to develop important capabilities that can be conferred as national viability. The country is rich in uranium, which it currently mines, with an estimated total of 244,788 tons in 33% of the national territory (BRASIL, 2007). Therefore, the natural resources required to achieve nuclear autonomy are abundant. Regarding human and technological resources, since 1975, with the agreement with West Germany, Brazil has sought to diversify its partnerships to reduce its dependency on the United States. During the Parallel Program, large investments were made to develop uranium enrichment technology domestically. The Navy, which developed research on the method of ultracentrifugation, was successful, and Brazil became a country capable of enriching uranium. The Parallel Program was an important step towards Brazil's nuclear autonomy (ANDRADE, 2006, p. 160). In terms of national viability, therefore, Brazil has the natural, human, and technological resources to achieve nuclear autonomy. </p>
    <p>The issue of international permissiveness is marked by pressures from the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) and central powers such as the United States. When Brazil signed the agreement with West Germany in 1975, the United States applied strong diplomatic pressure on Germany to cancel the deal (OLIVEIRA, 1991, p. 192; ANDRADE, 2006, p. 145). Additionally, in 2004, the IAEA raised suspicions about Brazil's uranium enrichment industry in Resende, as Brazil refused to allow Agency inspectors visual access to the enrichment centrifuges, citing the need to protect Brazilian industrial secrets (ANDRADE, 2006, p. 164).</p>
    <p>Currently, the biggest issue between Brazil and the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Regime concerns the IAEA's Additional Protocol. The Additional Protocol is a mechanism that allows the IAEA to inspect undeclared facilities in countries. For Brazil, this mechanism represents an intrusion level inconsistent with the values of national sovereignty and nuclear autonomy. Furthermore, Brazil criticizes the Additional Protocol as an additional burden on non-nuclear countries, while nuclear states fail to fulfill their nuclear disarmament obligations under the Non-Proliferation Treaty. The consequences of Brazil's refusal to sign the Additional Protocol have been ongoing discussions in the Nuclear Suppliers Group regarding the mandatory signature for participation in trade with member countries of the group (JONAS, CARLSON, GOOREVICH, 2015). In terms of international permissiveness, therefore, one can observe that Brazil faces some resistance from the nuclear powers' oligopoly to the development of its autonomous nuclear industry. The loss of this commercial oligopoly of nuclear materials and technologies, caused by the diffusion of these technologies to developing countries, may be a reason for the obstacles imposed by great powers to the peaceful nuclear development of peripheral countries. </p>
    <p>
      <bold>7.Overcoming the lack of trust and an apparent nuclear arms race</bold>
    </p>
    <p>During the late 20th century, both Brazil and Argentina avoided signing the NPT and criticized it as an unfair crystallization of world power, as well as defended their right to develop technology for peaceful nuclear explosions (PNEs). These two factors originated perceptions in central countries – especially the United States - that they might pursue nuclear weapons programs which could ultimately trigger an arms race in the region (PATTI, 2021; HYMANS, 2001). These perceptions were made evident during Brazil and West Germany’s nuclear deal in 1975, which would enable Brazil to master the entirety of the nuclear fuel cycle, when the United States protested it as part of its non-proliferation policy, and the analogous case involving Argentina and Canada (QUESTER, 1982; MENDOZA, 2005). </p>
    <p>Despite such external perceptions, Argentinian-Brazilian relations evolved towards trust and security mechanisms. The resolution of the Itaipu-Corpus dispute facilitated greater political will for rapprochement (LAFER, 1997; SPEKTOR, 2002; HIRST, 1991). Nuclear cooperation between Brazil and Argentina was a critical issue from de 1980s through the 1990s and is considered one of the greatest successes in the field of denuclearization and regional stability worldwide (QUEIROZ, 2016).</p>
    <p>Brazil and Argentina have similar nuclear trajectories; they began developing their nuclear industries around the same time and went through military dictatorships that accelerated nuclear development. The fact that both countries experienced significant development under military governments raised concerns in the international community about the militarization of their nuclear projects, with some international media and scientific communities suggesting a potential arms race and security dilemma between the two South American neighbors (QUEIROZ, 2016, p. 46).</p>
    <p>Since the transition to civilian governments and the efforts of researchers to unveil the domestic and foreign policies of military governments, the most accepted conclusions are that there was never an arms race or nuclear security dilemma between Brazil and Argentina (SPEKTOR, WHEELER, NEDAL, 2012; HYMANS, 2001). What was observed during the military governments were strong feelings of technological competitiveness, which were considerably caused by Argentina’s technological superiority during these decades.  This relative superiority was evident to Brazilian officials and was mainly due to Argentina’s early choices for natural uranium reactors, which diminished dependency on foreign enriched uranium (GOLDENBERG, ALVIM, MAFRA, 2018; QUEIROZ, 2016). The sentiment that marked the bilateral relationship during the military governments was, therefore, that of competitiveness for technological superiority in the region, not for nuclear deterrence capability. </p>
    <p>By the end of the military governments and the beginning of the democratization processes, significant steps toward nuclear cooperation occurred. In 1985, both countries committed to the peaceful use of nuclear energy and established the Nuclear Working Group (MALLEA, 2019). Civilian presidents José Sarney and Raúl Alfonsín fostered bilateral trust, evidenced by mutual transparency in uranium enrichment achievements through a series of official visits from each other’s presidents to each country’s enrichment facilities (MALLEA; SPEKTOR; WHEELER; 2012). This led to the creation of the Common System of Nuclear Material Accounting and Control (SCCC) in 1990, the Agreement for the Exclusively Peaceful Use of Nuclear Energy in 1991, and the creation of the first and, to this day, the only bilateral nuclear material control and accounting agency in the world: The Brazilian-Argentine Agency for Accounting and Control of Nuclear Materials (ABACC). The bilateral mechanisms between Brazil and Argentina built trust and transparency, satisfying international scrutiny and enabling nuclear cooperation with major suppliers (REDICK, 1995). We argue that the integration between Brazil and Argentina is an example of what Juan Carlos Puig defined as integration for autonomy.</p>
    <p>According to Queiroz (2016), three main elements underpinned the cooperation between the two countries: i) symmetry in the development of their programs, which encouraged engagement between them. The programs were at similar stages with comparable technological advances, allowing the countries to identify with each other. In other words, they had similar technological statuses in their nuclear programs; ii) a desire for autonomy, which entailed similar challenges and opportunities for both. Both countries actively sought autonomy in their nuclear industries, carrying with them similar values: autonomy, sovereignty, and nuclear disarmament. This shared value system led to similar stances between Brazil and Argentina in various forums and institutions of the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Regime: both refused to sign the Non-Proliferation Treaty when it opened in the late 1960s, signing only in the 1990s; both defended the right to peaceful nuclear explosions during discussions on the Tlatelolco Treaty; both currently refuse to sign the Additional Protocol on grounds related to sovereignty and the failure of nuclear powers to fulfill their nuclear bargaining commitments; iii) complementarity of their programs, as both sought to master enrichment technology through distinct means (QUEIROZ, 2016, p. 48). </p>
    <p>The bilateral nuclear cooperation and integration between Brazil and Argentina, founded on the similarities of status and values shared by both countries, also provide them with greater possibilities of political resistance against pressures from the great powers and institutions of the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Regime (SPEKTOR, 2017, p. 645). Jaguaribe stated that Brazil and Argentina are an important alliance to resist the general primacy of the United States, calling it a strategic alliance (JAGUARIBE, 2009). Integration, therefore, stands out as a vital instrument for the autonomy of both countries in relation to the great powers and their nuclear oligopoly.</p>
    <p>A fundamental point in discussions about nuclear cooperation and integration between Brazil and Argentina is the nature of the relationship between the two countries. Even during military governments, Brazil and Argentina had a relationship marked by rivalry, not enmity (QUEIROZ, 2016, p. 48; SUPPO, BRIZUELA, NUNES, 2016, p. 33). Despite speculation about proliferation and arms race in the region, Argentina and Brazil have consistently prioritized peaceful uses of nuclear energy, focusing on increasing autonomy and reducing technological dependence rather than developing nuclear weapons (SPEKTOR, WHEELER, NEDAL, 2012; HYMANS, 2001; CARASALES, 1999).</p>
    <p>
      <bold>8.Limits to the theory of nuclear autonomy: the problem of generalizability</bold>
    </p>
    <p>Because it is directly derivative of the theories of autonomy as put forward by Hélio Jaguaribe and Juan Carlos Puig, the theory of nuclear autonomy has similar limits and generalizability as its source. In this sense, there are two important shortcomings in an attempt to describe nuclear autonomy as a highly generalizable theory, hence why it is not the aim of this article. The first limit is due to the fundamental characteristic of autonomy as a political goal. The second limit is related to the lack of interstate and relative peaceful relations that characterize the region of South America. These are discussed as follows:</p>
    <p>In accordance with the differentiation put forth by Vigevani and Cepaluni, the concept of autonomy that is used in this article,, is predominantly related to peripheral countries and their policies. According to Helio Jaguaribe dedicates a considerable length of his seminal work <italic>“Autonomía periférica y hegemonía céntrica” </italic>(1979)to discuss the conditions under which peripheral countries might be able to overcome their status as dependent countries and acquire higher levels of autonomy. These are related to domestic contexts pertaining to industrial development and international characteristics pertaining to specific relations between central and peripheral countries, and how such relations allow for peripheral countries to ascend to autonomous capabilities. According to Jaguaribe, few countries can satisfy such prerequisites (1979, p. 129). This fundamental characteristic of a general theory of autonomy directly makes a theory of nuclear autonomy as pertaining to a limited number of countries. Nuclear autonomy, therefore, is best used as an analytical tool in countries with relatively high industrial development, usually characterized as semi-peripheral (See WALLERSTEIN, 1976) or newly industrializing countries (See HAGGARD, 1986).</p>
    <p>The second limit is related to an absence of an overall regional context of interstate conflict or the possibility of conflict that generally creates perceptions in countries of the region that they must attain nuclear weapons in order to guarantee deterrence capability from other countries’ aggressions. This is important because our efforts to argue that nuclear technology in South America has not been marked by traditional and military aspects of security do not exclude all the discussed works on nuclear weapons and their use in other regional contexts. That is to say that nuclear aspirations by Brazil and Argentina are not geared towards nuclear deterrence capability because there has not been a perception by each country that the other could pose existential threats that should be dealt with through nuclear deterrence. In fact, Buzan, Waever and Wilde (1998) describe Latin America as a region with significantly few incidents of interstate conflicts and considerably less affected by Cold War security dynamics<fn id="fn8"><label>9</label><p> The authors write that “military rivalries and tensions have been somewhat common” (BUZAN; WAEVER; WILDE, 1998, p. 68) in South America. We have argued that such rivalries are more accurately analyzed as scientific and technological competition between the two countries during their respective military governments, rather than a situation of a security dilemma.  </p></fn> - with the exception of Cuba. The authors state that since the end of the Cold War and democratization in the region, Latin America has enjoyed a “significant and sustained trend of desecuritization”, which includes the successful establishment of Latin America as a Nuclear-Weapons-Free Zone (BUZAN; WAEVER; WILDE, 1998, p. 68).</p>
    <p>In exposing such important prerequisites for the theory of nuclear autonomy, it becomes evident that there’s a considerably low level of generalizability for it. Few other regions in the world have a similar context of lack of interstate conflicts as well as peripheral countries with a sufficiently high level of industrialization. Analyses of countries such as Iran and North Korea have limited gains in applying the concept of nuclear autonomy because both countries are heavily influenced by regional contexts of military tension and perceptions of existential threats, to which nuclear deterrence theories play an important role. On the other hand, countries such as Peru and Venezuela, which are South American countries, are most likely to pursue other economic and energy-related goals than nuclear technology due to the high costs of such capital-intensive endeavor, having, as of writing, only purchased reactors for research purposes. </p>
    <p>This means that, at the present moment, nuclear autonomy has predominantly been an objective of Brazil and Argentina. We argue that the present framework is important in understanding the two countries’ nuclear policies in domestic and international affairs. Applications of this theory in other contexts are possible if countries fulfil the two conditions presented in this session. </p>
    <p>
      <bold>9.Conclusion</bold>
    </p>
    <p>Having laid out a critique of mainstream knowledge production in International Relations academia and the field of nuclear proliferation through instrumentalization of postcolonial and critical starting points, the constructivist contributions of the School of Copenhagen and the theoretical framework of the School of Autonomy, as well as discussing the history of nuclear technology development in South America, this work draws two remarks:</p>
    <p>The first remark is that mainstream theories and lenses that link the development of nuclear technology to intrinsic risks of proliferation of nuclear weapons and, therefore, to deterioration of regional and international stability and security have no observable applications in South America. Even when Brazil and Argentina were unchecked by international safeguards and were developing nuclear programs that sought indigenous technology, there is no evidence that a nuclear arms race was taking place that could have risked the stability of the region.</p>
    <p>The second remark is that autonomy theories make important contributions to the understanding of the nuclear field in South America. Jaguaribe’s stratification of the international system seems to accurately describe the relationship between nuclear powers that possess advanced technology and developing countries that seek to acquire it, the dependency that arises from this relation and the quest for overcoming this dependency. The concepts of national viability, international permissiveness and integration are useful tools to describe Brazil and Argentina’s histories of pursuing self-sufficiency in development and building nuclear technology as well as hindrances to that very objective imposed by the nuclear powers.</p>
    <p>We propose that the entirety of observable projects and policies executed by Brazil and Argentina, such as refusing to sign the NPT, defending the right for Peaceful Nuclear Explosions, cooperating with West Germany and Canada for the transfer of nuclear technology for mastering the fuel cycle, developing domestic projects unchecked by international verification mechanisms, and cooperating towards bilateral institutions for trust building, be understood as domestic and foreign policies towards nuclear autonomy, not nuclear weapons acquisition for nuclear deterrence capabilities. This work, therefore, defends the necessity that International Relations academia and scientific productions consider the possibility that not all domestic, regional and international contexts of nuclear development are accurately described by theories that privilege traditional security aspects and the intrinsic proliferation of nuclear weapons, but that some such contexts have specific and underlying aspects that are more accurately described by the quest for development and autonomy. </p>
    <p>
      <bold>References</bold>
    </p>
    <p>ALBORNOZ, Felipe. <bold>El proyecto de reactor CAREM</bold>. <italic>CNEA.gov</italic>, [S. l.], 9 maio 2018. p. 1. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/200907161">200907161</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/200907161">200907161</ext-link>. Acesso em: 5 jul. 2022.</p>
    <p>ALONSO, Matías. Alberto Lamagna: “El enriquecimiento de uranio es el soporte de las exportaciones nucleares”. <bold>Agencia TSS. La Agencia TSS. Tecnología Sur-Sur</bold>. [S. l.], 24 jul. 2019. p. 1. Entrevista concedida. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.agenciatss.com.ar/alberto-lamagna-el-enriquecimiento-de-uranio-es-el-soporte-de-las-exportaciones-nucleares/">https://www.agenciatss.com.ar/alberto-lamagna-el-enriquecimiento-de-uranio-es-el-soporte-de-las-exportaciones-nucleares/</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.agenciatss.com.ar/alberto-lamagna-el-enriquecimiento-de-uranio-es-el-soporte-de-las-exportaciones-nucleares/">https://www.agenciatss.com.ar/alberto-lamagna-el-enriquecimiento-de-uranio-es-el-soporte-de-las-exportaciones-nucleares/</ext-link>. Acesso em: 18 nov. 2024.</p>
    <p>ANDRADE, Ana Maria Ribeiro de. <bold>A opção nuclear</bold>: 50 anos rumo à autonomia. 1. ed. Rio de Janeiro: Museu de Astronomia e Ciências Afins, 2006. 189 p.</p>
    <p>ARGENTINA. Comisión Nacional de Energía Atómica. <bold>Informe especial sobre el uranio</bold>. Buenos Aires: Comisión Nacional de Energía Atómica, 2016. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.argentina.gob.ar/sites/default/files/diciembre_2016_-_informe_especial_de_uranio_0.pdf">https://www.argentina.gob.ar/sites/default/files/diciembre_2016_-_informe_especial_de_uranio_0.pdf</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.argentina.gob.ar/sites/default/files/diciembre_2016_-_informe_especial_de_uranio_0.pdf">https://www.argentina.gob.ar/sites/default/files/diciembre_2016_-_informe_especial_de_uranio_0.pdf</ext-link>. Acesso em: 13 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>ARGENTINA. Ministerio de Energía y Minería. <bold>Escenarios Energéticos 2030</bold>. Buenos Aires: Ministerio de Energía y Minería, 2019. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://datos.energia.gob.ar/dataset/escenarios-energeticos">http://datos.energia.gob.ar/dataset/escenarios-energeticos</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://datos.energia.gob.ar/dataset/escenarios-energeticos">http://datos.energia.gob.ar/dataset/escenarios-energeticos</ext-link>. Acesso em: 13 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>ARGÜELLO, Irma. The Position of an Emerging Global Power: Brazilian Responses to the 2010 US Nuclear Posture Review. <bold>Nonproliferation Review</bold>, v. 18, n. 1, p. 183-200, 2011. DOI: 10.1080/10736700.2011.549180.</p>
    <p>BALBINO, Tomás. Cooperación nuclear argentino brasileña 1985- 2015: un caso de cooperación Sur-Sur. <bold>Defensa Nacional</bold>, Buenos Aires, n. 2, p. 29-52, 2019. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/1847939">1847939</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/1847939">1847939</ext-link>. Acesso em: 17 mar. 2022.</p>
    <p>BELL, Mark S.; MILLER, Nicholas L. Questioning the effect of nuclear weapons on conflict. In: NARANG, Neil; GARTZKE, Erik; KROENIG, Matthew (ed.). <bold>Nonproliferation Policy and Nuclear Posture</bold>: Causes and consequences for the spread of nuclear weapons. 1. ed. Princeton, New Jersey: Routledge, 2016. cap. 12, p. 295-312.</p>
    <p>BLAUMANN, Hermán et al. RA-10: A New argentinian multipurpose research reactor. In: INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON RESEARCH REACTORS: SAFE MANAGEMENT AND EFFECTIVE UTILIZATION, 4., 2011, Rabat Morocco. <bold>Electronic Proceedings</bold> [...]. Viena, Austria: International Atomic Energy Agency, 2012. Tema: SPECIFIC NUCLEAR REACTORS AND ASSOCIATED PLANTS (S21). Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www-pub.iaea.org/MTCD/publications/PDF/P1575_CD_web/datasets/papers/C4%20Blaumann.pdf">https://www-pub.iaea.org/MTCD/publications/PDF/P1575_CD_web/datasets/papers/C4%20Blaumann.pdf</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www-pub.iaea.org/MTCD/publications/PDF/P1575_CD_web/datasets/papers/C4%20Blaumann.pdf">https://www-pub.iaea.org/MTCD/publications/PDF/P1575_CD_web/datasets/papers/C4%20Blaumann.pdf</ext-link>. Acesso em: 18 nov. 2024.</p>
    <p>BRASIL. Ministério de Minas e Energia. <bold>Plano Nacional de Energia 2030</bold>. Brasília: Empresa de Pesquisa Energética, 2007. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epe.gov.br/pt/publicacoes-dados-abertos/publicacoes/Plano-Nacional-de-Energia-PNE-2030">https://www.epe.gov.br/pt/publicacoes-dados-abertos/publicacoes/Plano-Nacional-de-Energia-PNE-2030</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epe.gov.br/pt/publicacoes-dados-abertos/publicacoes/Plano-Nacional-de-Energia-PNE-2030">https://www.epe.gov.br/pt/publicacoes-dados-abertos/publicacoes/Plano-Nacional-de-Energia-PNE-2030</ext-link>. Acesso em: 10 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>BRICEÑO RUIZ, José; SIMONOFF, Alejandro. La Escuela de la Autonomía, América Latina y la teoría de las relaciones internacionales. <bold>Estudios internacionales (Santiago)</bold>, v. 49, n. 186, p. 39-89, 2017.</p>
    <p>BUZAN, Barry; HANSEN, Lene. <bold>The evolution of international security studies</bold>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009.</p>
    <p>BUZAN, Barry; WÆVER, Ole. <bold>Regions and Powers</bold>: The Structure of International Security. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003.</p>
    <p>BUZAN, Barry; WÆVER, Ole; DE WILDE, Jaap. <bold>Security</bold>: A New Framework for Analysis. Boulder, Colorado, United States: Lynne Rienner Publishers, 1998.</p>
    <p>CABLE, Vincent. What is international economic security?. <bold>International Affairs</bold>, vol. 71, n. 2, p. 305-324, 1995. DOI: 10.2307/2623436.</p>
    <p>CABRERA-PALMER, Belkis; ROTHWELL, Geoffrey. Why is Brazil enriching uranium?. <bold>Energy Policy</bold>, v. 36, n. 7, p. 2570-2577, 2008.</p>
    <p>CARASALES, Julio C. The so‐called proliferator that wasn't: The story of Argentina's nuclear policy. <bold>The Nonproliferation Review</bold>, v. 6, n. 4, p. 51-64, 1999. DOI: 10.1080/10736709908436778.</p>
    <p>CARASALES, Julio C. The so‐called proliferator that wasn't: The story of Argentina's nuclear policy. <bold>The Nonproliferation Review</bold>, v. 6, n. 4, p. 51-64, 1999. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nonproliferation.org/wp-content/uploads/npr/carasa64.pdf">https://www.nonproliferation.org/wp-content/uploads/npr/carasa64.pdf</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nonproliferation.org/wp-content/uploads/npr/carasa64.pdf">https://www.nonproliferation.org/wp-content/uploads/npr/carasa64.pdf</ext-link>. Acesso em: 13 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>COLOMBO, Sandra; GUGLIELMINOTTI, Cristian; VERA, María Nevia. El desarrollo nuclear de Argentina y el régimen de no proliferación. <bold>Perfiles latinoamericanos</bold>, v. 25, n. 49, p. 119-139, 2017. DOI: 10.18504/pl2549-006-2017.</p>
    <p>DENZA, Eileen. Non-proliferation of nuclear weapons: The European Union and Iran. <bold>Eur. Foreign Aff. Rev.</bold>, v. 10, p. 289, 2005.</p>
    <p>DIEHL, Sarah; FUJII, Eduardo. Brazil's New National Defense Strategy Calls for Strategic Nuclear Developments. <bold>NTI website</bold>, 2009.</p>
    <p>DUNLAP, Christopher Thomas. <bold>Parallel Power Play: Nuclear Technology and Diplomacy in Argentina and Brazil, 1945-1995</bold>. 2017. 360 f. Tese (Doctor of Philosophy) - THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, Chicago, Illinois, 2017. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/46036">46036</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/46036">46036</ext-link>. Acesso em: 20 jan. 2022.</p>
    <p>GOLDEMBERG, José. Nuclear energy in developing countries. <bold>Daedalus</bold>, v. 138, n. 4, p. 71-80, 2009. DOI: 10.1162/daed.2009.138.4.71.</p>
    <p>GOLDEMBERG, José; FEU ALVIM, Carlos; MAFRA, Olga Y. The denuclearization of Brazil and Argentina. <bold>Journal for Peace and Nuclear Disarmament</bold>, v. 1, n. 2, p. 383-403, 2018. DOI: 10.1080/25751654.2018.1479129.</p>
    <p>HAGGARD, Stephan. The Newly Industrializing Countries in the International System. <bold>World Politics</bold>, v. 38, n. 2, p. 343-370, jan. 1986. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/95320">95320</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/95320">95320</ext-link>. Acesso em: 13 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>HERZ, Mônica; DAWOOD, Layla; LAGE, Victor Coutinho. A Nuclear Submarine in the South Atlantic: The Framing of Threats and Deterrence. <bold>Contexto Internacional</bold>, v. 39, p. 329-350, 2017.</p>
    <p>HIRST, Monica. O programa de integração Argentina-Brasil: concepção original e ajustes crescentes. In: <bold>Cone Sul</bold>: A economia política de integração. Rio de Janeiro: Funcex, 1991.</p>
    <p>HOPF, Ted. The promise of constructivism in international relations theory. <bold>International security</bold>, vol. 23, n. 1, p. 171-200, 1998. DOI: 10.1162/isec.23.1.171.</p>
    <p>HURTADO, Diego. <bold>El sueño de la Argentina atómica</bold>. Política, tecnología nuclear y desarrollo nacional (1945-2006). Buenos Aires: Edhasa, 2014.</p>
    <p>HYMANS, Jacques EC. Of gauchos and gringos: Why Argentina never wanted the bomb, and why the United States thought it did. <bold>Security Studies</bold>, v. 10, n. 3, p. 153-185, 2001. DOI: 10.1080/09636410108429440.</p>
    <p>JAGUARIBE, Helio. Autonomía periférica y hegemonía céntrica. <bold>Estudios internacionales</bold>, p. 91-130, 1979. Disponível em: [link suspeito removido]. Acesso em: 18 nov. 2024.</p>
    <p>JESUS, Diego Santos Vieira de. Noites tropicais: o Brasil e a nova era da não proliferação e do desarmamento nucleares (2003-2010). <bold>Revista de Sociologia e Política</bold>, v. 20, p. 43-57, 2012. DOI: 10.1590/S0104-44782012000300003.</p>
    <p>KAHLER, Miles. Economic security in an era of globalization: definition and provision. <bold>The Pacific Review</bold>, vol. 17, n. 4, p. 485-502, 2004. DOI: 10.1080/0951274042000326032.</p>
    <p>KEOHANE, Robert O. <bold>After Hegemony</bold>: cooperation and discord in the world political economy. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1984.</p>
    <p>KEOHANE, Robert O.; NYE JR, Joseph S. Power and interdependence. <bold>Survival</bold>, v. 15, n. 4, p. 158-165, 1973. DOI: 10.1080/00396337308441409.</p>
    <p>KLARE, Michael T. Energy Security. In: WILLIAMS, Paul D. (ed.). <bold>Security Studies</bold>: An Introduction. 2. ed. New York, NY: Routledge, 2013. cap. 35, p. 535-554.</p>
    <p>LAFER, Celso. Relações Brasil-Argentina: alcance e significado de uma parceria estratégica. <bold>Contexto Internacional</bold>, v. 19, n. 2, p. 249, 1997.</p>
    <p>LAFFEY, Mark; WELDES, Jutta. Decolonizing the Cuban missile crisis. <bold>International Studies Quarterly</bold>, v. 52, n. 3, p. 555-577, 2008.</p>
    <p>LINKLATER, Andrew. 13 The achievements of critical theory. In: SMITH, Steve; BOOTH, Ken; ZALEWSKI, Marysia (ed.). <bold>International theory</bold>: Positivism and beyond. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996. p. 279-288. DOI: 10.1017/CBO9780511660054.015.</p>
    <p>LUGONES, Manuel José; VERA, Nevia. Los programas nucleoeléctricos de Argentina, Brasil y México: Un estudio comparativo de estrategias de desarrollo tecnológico. <bold>Revista Iberoamericana de Ciencia, Tecnología y Sociedad - CTS</bold>, [S. l.], v. 19, n. 57, p. 79–104, 2023. DOI: 10.52712/issn.1850-0013-349. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ojs.revistacts.net/index.php/CTS/article/view/349">https://ojs.revistacts.net/index.php/CTS/article/view/349</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ojs.revistacts.net/index.php/CTS/article/view/349">https://ojs.revistacts.net/index.php/CTS/article/view/349</ext-link>. Acesso em: 18 nov. 2024.</p>
    <p>MALLEA, Rodrigo. Claves históricas de la identidad nuclear argentino-brasileña. <bold>Defensa Nacional (Revista Científica)</bold>, Argentina, n. 3, p. 1-16, 2019. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/1847939">1847939</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/1847939">1847939</ext-link>. Acesso em: 21 jan. 2022.</p>
    <p>MALLEA, Rodrigo; SPEKTOR, Matias; WHEELER, Nicholas J. <bold>Origens da cooperação nuclear</bold>: Uma história oral crítica entre Argentina e Brasil. 1. ed. Rio de Janeiro: Woodrow Wilson Center for Scholars e Fundação Getúlio Vargas, 2012. 240 p.</p>
    <p>MARTINS FILHO, João Roberto. O projeto do submarino nuclear brasileiro. <bold>Contexto Internacional</bold>, v. 33, p. 277-314, 2011.</p>
    <p>MEARSHEIMER, John J. The case for a Ukrainian nuclear deterrent. <bold>Foreign affairs</bold>, p. 50-66, 1993.</p>
    <p>MENDOZA, Diego Hurtado de. De “átomos para la paz” a los reactores de potencia: Tecnología y política nuclear en la Argentina (1955-1976). <bold>Revista CTS</bold>, v. 2, n. 4, p. 41-66, jan. 2005. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.scielo.org.ar/pdf/cts/v2n4/v2n4a03.pdf">https://www.scielo.org.ar/pdf/cts/v2n4/v2n4a03.pdf</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.scielo.org.ar/pdf/cts/v2n4/v2n4a03.pdf">https://www.scielo.org.ar/pdf/cts/v2n4/v2n4a03.pdf</ext-link>. Acesso em: 13 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>MILLER, Steven E.; SAGAN, Scott D. Nuclear power without nuclear proliferation?. <bold>Daedalus</bold>, v. 138, n. 4, p. 7-18, 2009.</p>
    <p>MONTEIRO, Nuno P.; DEBS, Alexandre. The strategic logic of nuclear proliferation. <bold>International Security</bold>, v. 39, n. 2, p. 7-51, 2014.</p>
    <p>NESADURAI, Helen ES. Introduction: economic security, globalization and governance. <bold>The Pacific Review</bold>, vol. 17, n. 4, p. 459-484, 2004. DOI: 10.1080/0951274042000326023.</p>
    <p>NICONILI GABRIEL, João Paulo. A Shortcut to Autonomy or a Path to Dependency? Foreign Assistance and Brazil’s Search for Nuclear Autonomy. <bold>The International Spectator</bold>, v. 58, n. 4, p. 55-72, 2023. DOI: 10.1080/03932729.2023.2219810.</p>
    <p>NYE, Joseph S. Maintaining a nonproliferation regime. <bold>International Organization</bold>, p. 15-38, 1981.</p>
    <p>OLIVEIRA, Odete Maria de. <bold>Os descaminhos do Brasil nuclear</bold>. Orientador: Christian Caubet. 1991. 961 f. Tese (Doutorado em Ciências Humanas - Especialidade Direito) - Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina, Florianópolis, 1991. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/123456789">123456789</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/123456789">123456789</ext-link>. Acesso em: 13 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>ONUF, Nicholas Greenwood. <bold>World of Our Making</bold>: Rules and rule in social theory and international relations. 2. ed. New York, NY: Routledge, 2012.</p>
    <p>ORNSTEIN, Roberto. El desarrollo nuclear argentino: 60 años de una historia exitosa. <bold>Publicación de la CNEA</bold>, n. 37, 2010.</p>
    <p>PATTI, Carlo. <bold>Brazil in the Global Nuclear Order 1945–2018</bold>. 1. ed. Maryland: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2021. v. 1. E-book.</p>
    <p>PUIG, Juan Carlos. Integración y autonomía de América Latina en las postrimerías del siglo XX. <bold>Integración Latinoamericana</bold>, v. 11, n. 109, p. 40-62, 1986.</p>
    <p>QUEIROZ, João Marcelo Galvão de. O modelo ABACC: Um balanço. In: CANTO, Odilon Antonio Marcuzzo do. <bold>O modelo ABACC</bold>: Um marco no desenvolvimento das relações entre Brasil e Argentina. 1. ed. Santa Maria: Editora UFSM, 2016. cap. 3, p. 61-78.</p>
    <p>QUESTER, George H. Nuclear Proliferation in Latin America. <bold>Current History</bold>, vol. 81, n. 472, p. 52-55, 1982. Disponível em: [link suspeito removido]. Acesso em: 13 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>REDICK, John R. <bold>Nuclear Illusions</bold>: Argentina and Brazil. Washington: The Henry L. Stimson Center, 1995. 61 p.</p>
    <p>REDICK, John R.; CARASALES, Julio C.; WROBEL, Paulo S. Nuclear rapprochement: Argentina, Brazil, and the nonproliferation regime. <bold>Washington Quarterly</bold>, v. 18, n. 1, p. 107-122, 1995.</p>
    <p>ROSA, Luiz Pinguelli. Geração hidrelétrica, termelétrica e nuclear. <bold>Estudos Avançados</bold>, v. 21, p. 39-58, 2007.</p>
    <p>SANTORO, Daniel. Una tecnología que puede servir para construir bombas atómicas: La Argentina volvió a enriquecer uranio después de 32 años. <bold>Clarín</bold>, [S. l.], 30 nov. 2015. Política, p. 1. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.clarin.com/politica/cristina-nuclear-pilcaniyeu_0_BJSoJtPml.html">https://www.clarin.com/politica/cristina-nuclear-pilcaniyeu_0_BJSoJtPml.html</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.clarin.com/politica/cristina-nuclear-pilcaniyeu_0_BJSoJtPml.html">https://www.clarin.com/politica/cristina-nuclear-pilcaniyeu_0_BJSoJtPml.html</ext-link>. Acesso em: 13 jul. 2022.</p>
    <p>SIMONOFF, Alejandro; LORENZINI, María Elena. Autonomía e integración en las teorías del sur: desentrañando el pensamiento de Hélio Jaguaribe y Juan Carlos Puig. <bold>Iberoamericana–Nordic Journal of Latin American and Caribbean Studies</bold>, v. 48, n. 1, 2019.</p>
    <p>SNYDER, Glenn H. <bold>Deterrence and Defense</bold>: TOWARD A THEORY OF NATIONAL SECURITY. 1. ed. Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 1961. 305 p.</p>
    <p>SPEKTOR, Matias. Brazil’s nuclear naval fuel: choices and a road map for productive engagement. In: <bold>Reducing risks from naval nuclear fuel</bold>. Washington, DC: Institute for International Science and Technology Policy, 2018. p. 21-27. Disponível em:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nonproliferation.org/reducing-risks-from-naval-nuclear-fuel/">https://nonproliferation.org/reducing-risks-from-naval-nuclear-fuel/</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nonproliferation.org/reducing-risks-from-naval-nuclear-fuel/">https://nonproliferation.org/reducing-risks-from-naval-nuclear-fuel/</ext-link>. Acesso em: 13 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>SPEKTOR, Matias. O Brasil e a Argentina entre a cordialidade oficial e o projeto de integração: a política externa do governo de Ernesto Geisel (1974-1979). <bold>Revista Brasileira de Política Internacional</bold>, v. 45, p. 117-145, 2002.</p>
    <p>STRITZEL, Holger. Towards a theory of securitization: Copenhagen and beyond. <bold>European journal of international relations</bold>, v. 13, n. 3, p. 357-383, 2007. DOI: 10.1177/1354066107080128.</p>
    <p>VERA, María N. <bold>La reactivación de la industria nuclear argentina (2006-2011)</bold>. 2013. Tese (Tesis para alcanzar el grado de licenciada en Relaciones Internacionales) - Universidad Nacional del Centro de la Provincia de Buenos Aires, Facultad de Ciencias Humanas, [S. l.], 2013.</p>
    <p>VERA, María; COLOMBO, Sandra. La política nuclear durante el gobierno de Néstor Kirchner (2003–2007). In: ENCUENTRO DEL CERPI Y JORNADA DEL CENSUD, 5., 3., 2011, La Plata, Argentina. <bold>Anais</bold> [...]. La Plata, Argentina: IRI UNLP, 2011. p. 1-27.</p>
    <p>VIGEVANI, Tullo; CEPALUNI, Gabriel. <bold>A política externa brasileira</bold>: a busca da autonomia, de Sarney a Lula. São Paulo: Editora UNESP, 2011.</p>
    <p>VISKI, Andrea. The revised nuclear suppliers group guidelines: a european union perspective. <bold>EU Non-Proliferation Consortium The European network of independent non-proliferation think tanks</bold>, [s. l.], n. 15, maio 2012.</p>
    <p>WALLERSTEIN, Immanuel. Semi-Peripheral Countries and the Contemporary World Crisis. <bold>Theory and Society</bold>, v. 3, n. 4, p. 461-483, 1976. Disponível em: [link suspeito removido]. Acesso em: 13 dez. 2024.</p>
    <p>WALTZ, Kenneth N. <bold>The spread of nuclear weapons</bold>: More may be better: Introduction. 1981.</p>
    <p>WALTZ, Kenneth. <bold>Theory of International Politics</bold>. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1979.</p>
    <p>WENDT, Alexander. Anarchy is what states make of it: the social construction of power politics. <bold>International organization</bold>, vol. 46, n. 2, p. 391-425, 1992. DOI: 10.1017/S0020818300027764.</p>
    <p>WOLDE-RUFAEL, Yemane; MENYAH, Kojo. Nuclear energy consumption and economic growth in nine developed countries. <bold>Energy economics</bold>, v. 32, n. 3, p. 550-556, 2010.</p>
    <p>YERGIN, Daniel. Ensuring Energy Security. <bold>Foreign Affairs</bold>, [s. l.], v. 85, n. 2, p. 69-82, 2006. Disponível em: [link suspeito removido]. Acesso em: 10 dez. 2024.</p>
  </body>
  <back/>
</article>
