<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.1" specific-use="sps-1.9">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
    <!-- OBRIGATORIO -->
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Revista BJLAS</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>

    <!-- OBRIGATORIO -->
    <article-meta>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>
      <bold>AS ANIMAL AS HUMAN. PORTRAYING THE WEREWOLF TOGETHER WITH THE </bold>
      <bold>
        <italic>QOM </italic>
      </bold>
      <bold>O</bold>
      <bold>F THE GRAN CHACO</bold>
    </p>
    <p>
      <italic>TAN ANIMAL, TAN HUMANO. RETRATANDO AL HOMBRE LOBO JUNTO A LOS QOM DEL GRAN CHACO</italic>
    </p>
    <p>
      <italic>TÃO ANIMAL, TÃO HUMANO: RETRATANDO O LOBISOMEM JUNTO A OS QOM DO GRAN CHACO</italic>
    </p>
    <p>
      <italic>Celeste Medrano</italic>
      <fn id="fn0">
        <label>1</label>
        <p> PhD in Anthropology. CONICET (National Council for Scientific and Technical Research). ICA, Institute of Anthropological Sciences, University of Buenos Aires. SPECTRA (Laboratory of Speculative Anthropology). Email: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="mailto:zoocosmologia@gmail.com">zoocosmologia@gmail.com</ext-link></p>
      </fn>
      <italic>
        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1475-9806"/>
      </italic>
    </p>
    <p>Universidad de Buenos Aires, Argentina</p>
    <p><bold>Abstract:</bold> This article is based on ethnographic observations made while studying human-animal relations among the <italic>Qom</italic> (Toba), an Indigenous group inhabiting the Gran Chaco region in northeastern Argentina. During this research, I encountered the figure of the werewolf among the <italic>Qom</italic>. However, fieldwork led me to hypothesize the existence of multiple forms of the werewolf, each enacted differently across the diverse ontological and social worlds that I observed. Using first-hand ethnographic material, this study analyzes the processes and characteristics that constitute the <italic>human–Qom–werewolf</italic> transformation. Understanding this metamorphosis requires engaging with <italic>Qom </italic>notions of animality, embodiment, and the porous boundaries between humans, animals, and other-than-human beings. Finally, the article situates <italic>Qom </italic>werewolves in dialogue with other regional representations of werewolves (Indigenous, Creole, and urban),  aiming to elucidate the concepts of humanity and animality operative within <italic>Qom </italic>sociocosmology and to compare them with analogous conceptual frameworks across South America.</p>
    <p><bold>Keywords: </bold>Werewolf; Animality; Humanity; Transformation; Indigenous People.</p>
    <p><bold>Resumen:</bold> Este artículo se basa en un hecho interesante que surgió cuando estaba aprendiendo sobre animales mientras trabajaba con el pueblo <italic>Qom</italic> (Tobas), un grupo indígena asentado en la región noreste argentina conocida como el Gran Chaco. Específicamente, me encontré con el hombre lobo. Sin embargo, comencé a sospechar la existencia de múltiples hombres lobo recreando los diversos mundos que estaba trayendo a conversación durante mi trabajo de campo etnográfico. Luego, a lo largo de esta contribución y analizando material etnográfico de primera mano, profundizo en las diferentes características que informan la transformación “humano-<italic>Qom</italic>-hombre lobo”. Para comprender tal metamorfosis, es necesario recurrir a las ideas sobre la animalidad que aprendí con los <italic>Qom</italic>. Finalmente, la propuesta concluye poniendo en conversación a hombres lobo (indígenas, criollos, etc.). El objetivo es delinear las ideas de humanidad y animalidad que el mundo <italic>Qom</italic> condensa en perspectiva con ideas similares que están integradas en otros mundos sudamericanos.</p>
    <p><bold>Palabras claves:</bold> Hombres Lobo; Animalidad; Humanidad; Transformación; Pueblos Indígenas.</p>
    <p><bold>Resumo:</bold> Este artigo surge de uma observação etnográfica realizada enquanto estudava as relações entre humanos e animais entre os <italic>Qom</italic> (Tobas), um grupo indígena que habita a região do Gran Chaco, no nordeste da Argentina. Durante esta pesquisa, deparei-me com a figura do lobisomem. No entanto, o trabalho de campo levou-me a hipotetizar a existência de múltiplas formas de lobisomem, cada uma representada de maneira diferente nos diversos mundos ontológicos e sociais que observei. Com base em material etnográfico de primeira mão, este estudo analisa os distintos processos e características que constituem a transformação <italic>humano–Qom–lobisomem</italic>. Compreender esta forma de metamorfose exige engajar-se com as noções <italic>Qom</italic> de animalidade, encarnação e os limites porosos entre humanos, animais e outros seres não humanos. Finalmente, o artigo situa os lobisomens <italic>Qom</italic> em diálogo com outras representações regionais do lobisomem (indígenas, crioulas e urbanas), com o objetivo de elucidar os conceitos de humanidade e animalidade presentes na sociocosmologia <italic>Qom</italic> e compará-los com estruturas conceituais análogas em outros contextos da América do Sul.</p>
    <p><bold>Palavras-chave:</bold> Lobisomem; Animalidade; Humanidade; Transformação; Povos Indígenas.</p>
    <p> DOI:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.11606/issn.1676-6288.prolam.2025.239481">10.11606/issn.1676-6288.prolam.2025.239481</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.11606/issn.1676-6288.prolam.2025.239481">10.11606/issn.1676-6288.prolam.2025.239481</ext-link></p>
    <p>
      <italic>Recebido em: 24/07/2025</italic>
    </p>
    <p>
      <italic>Aprovado em: 29/12/2025</italic>
    </p>
    <p>
      <italic>Publicado em: 29/12/2025</italic>
    </p>
    <p>
      <bold>1.Introduction</bold>
    </p>
    <p>On a November morning in 2009, while I was working with Mauricio Maidana —a <italic>Qom</italic> <italic>laqta’q</italic> teacher and former hunter— on the manuscript that would later become <italic>Qom </italic>Zoology (MEDRANO; MAIDANA; GÓMEZ, 2011), I naively asked whether the <italic>aguará guazú</italic> (<italic>Chrysocyon brachyurus</italic>) was believed to foretell anything, noting that some Creole people (Argentines and Brazilians) compare it to a werewolf. Mauricio replied categorically: “No —the werewolf is something else.” He then continued, “In the Chaco, there are several places where werewolves exist. I am going to tell you a little about them.”</p>
    <p>This contribution is grounded in that act of invention (in the Wagnerian sense)<fn id="fn1"><label>2</label><p> Roy Wagner mentions that “an anthropologist ‘invents’ the culture he believes himself to be studying, and that the relation is more ‘real’ for being his particular acts and experiences than the things it ‘relates’” (1981, p. 13). Thus, for Wagner, ‘invention’ is a process that occurs objectively, through observation and learning, rather than as a form of free fantasy: “In the act of inventing another culture, the anthropologist invents his own, and in fact he reinvents the notion of culture itself” (WAGNER, 1981 [1975], p. 14).</p></fn>, which emerged while I was learning about the animals known to the <italic>Qom</italic> (Toba) people —an Indigenous group historically settled in the northeastern Argentine region known as the Gran Chaco. In the course of this process, I found myself drawn to such a singular creature. In order to assemble the figure of the werewolf that Mauricio had introduced to me, however, I repeatedly drew upon specific features of Indigenous sociocosmology that I had learned both prior to and following that conversation, through successive and extended periods of fieldwork in communities located in eastern Formosa Province.<fn id="fn2"><label>3</label><p> I conducted ethnographic fieldwork between 2008 and 2024 in several Qom communities in the Formosa and Chaco provinces, Argentina. In this article, I present notes and accounts gathered in Riacho de Oro, San Carlos, and Kilómetro 503 of the Patiño and El Desaguadero departments; El Naranjito; the Toba neighborhood Nlaxayec (La Paz); and 12 de Octubre (located in the common urban land of El Colorado city) of the Pirané department, Formosa Province; as well as accounts gathered in the El Chorro region, part of the Meguesoxoche 140,000 ha of the Chaco province.</p></fn> </p>
    <p>Animal or human? Man-wolf or wolf-man? Victim or victimizer? I began to suspect the existence of multiple werewolves, enacted across the diverse worlds that came into conversation during my fieldwork. The <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf did not appear to be the same as those of my childhood imaginings, nor as the one recognized by Creole people. My own, in particular, was the seventh son of an exclusively male lineage, whose ontogenetic tragedy had historically motivated presidential patronage. Accordingly, in this article I present my inquiries into the werewolf as a creature that is at once animal and human.</p>
    <p>First, I summarize key aspects of <italic>Qom</italic> human–animal transformation. I then briefly outline the broader Indigenous background that situates and explains these transformations. This allows me to further nuance the discussion. Hence, throughout the article I draw not only on the animality ideas I have learned with the <italic>Qom </italic>but also engage with Indigenous notions of body and personhood, etiological systems, relations with non-humans (animals and plants, owners of animal species and spaces such as the bush, the field, or even the water), and cosmology. These domains are brought into analytical focus by the werewolf as both animal and human. Second, I examine historical materials that allow me to sketch the figure of the werewolf as it appears in Creole and rural South American worlds. Finally, inspired by Lévi-Strauss —who argued that the hypothesis of a “pure and simple loan is untenable” (LÉVI-STRAUSS, 1992, p. 39, <italic>our translation</italic>)— I bring into conversation werewolves described in different ethnographic works and specialized literature. These include Indigenous, Creole, Portuguese, and European contexts. The article ultimately aims to outline <italic>Qom</italic> ideas of humanity and animality in dialogue with analogous concepts embedded in other worlds<fn id="fn3"><label>4</label><p> Preliminary reflections on the topic addressed in this work were published in Medrano (2022).</p></fn>.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>2.Turning into a </bold>
      <bold>
        <italic>Qom </italic>
      </bold>
      <bold>werewolf </bold>
    </p>
    <p>Returning to the initial question that opened this article, I will now elaborate on what Mauricio Maidana revealed to me during that November morning full of <italic>mate</italic> and misunderstandings:</p>
    <p>Because that one [the <italic>aguará guazú</italic>] is an animal, it is not a werewolf, the werewolf is another one. Sometimes, the werewolf is a ghost, because sometimes [it is a] person that wanders at night, eats spoiled meat; because inside has a spirit, […] that one turns into an animal and wanders at night. And, according to what an old man had told [me], when the werewolf comes out, he is always in the middle of the road, like that, and perhaps a person comes there, toward him, and they collide and he enters [between the legs]; then it all starts there, then hegets inside the person and that person becomes an animal, when the time arrives, because hehas his time (<italic>literal translation</italic>).<fn id="fn4"><label>5</label><p> We have opted for a literal, or close-to-the-original, translation of the interlocutors’ accounts. A strictly naturalistic rendering of their speech would inevitably obscure the specific tone, cadence, and discursive logic under which these narratives were collected. This approach ensures greater fidelity to the original ethnographic texture.</p></fn></p>
    <p>Although both my previous readings and the information I had treasured during my childhood indicate that, most of the time, Creole and rural people see the werewolf in the <italic>aguará guazu</italic>, Mauricio’s words and other <italic>Qom</italic> stories show that the <italic>Qom</italic> would never mistake the <italic>qa’alaq</italic> (<italic>aguará guazú</italic>) for the wolf-man. As Félix Suárez explained to me a few years later:</p>
    <p>At least for us, that one [<italic>aguará guazú</italic>] is not a werewolf. Yes, because I saw a werewolf, a person. When we were harvesting there [in] Porteñito […]. And well, we had a buddy, we were harvesters, it seems that guy did not hide the power he has, and also has the wife. And that guy says that a bad spirit came, it got into the man, and he says he jumps, he jumps three times, a dog takes form there, a big dog. And when that man goes out, he says he comes to Porteñito and he goes to Bartolomé (<italic>literal translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>The first narratives I gathered about <italic>Qom</italic> werewolves indicated that, in their human phase, they were very old people who slept during the day and came out at night. They had a sickly appearance and could not establish marital relationships with women. People told me, for example: “There, in Laishí, there is one; he is an old man,” “That one you saw passing by was a werewolf, but he recovered,” and “It was very noticeable that he was a werewolf because he was thin and [he had] all his eyes with that eye disease, yellow pus.” As I continued my research, however, I encountered werewolves who led more familiar, everyday lives. Some of them even had a ‘wife’ and children. As I will explain later, the <italic>Qom</italic> suggest that these children were probably conceived either before acquiring the power of the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf or after recovering from it. Despite their unhealthy and thin appearance —likely related to a poor diet— several werewolves participated in work activities. As Valentín Suárez explained to me:</p>
    <p>That one used to work, go to the grocery store and buy mortadella, canned meat and bread, but he didn’t eat; otherwise, he went to the house and opened everything, the can of meat, and let all the food go off, and only then he would eat, everything, when the food was already spoiled (<italic>literal translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>The <italic>Qom</italic> describe the werewolf as always associated with a family or community during its human phase. They explicitly state that “he has a domain” and link him to a home from which he departs when it is time to transform into an animal, or to which he returns when he becomes human again. For a <italic>Qom</italic> <italic>lashe</italic> (a <italic>Qom</italic> woman), her husband’s nocturnal movements and unusual requests often raised suspicion. He would say, for example: “We mustn’t close the door, we mustn’t close [it], ma’am… because it is too hot.” She would respond: “Why do we leave it open? What if something comes in, a critter, and hides inside our house?” Eventually, she decided to spy on her husband and discovered that he transformed every night into a large black dog. She concluded, according to Vilo Viejo’s reconstruction of events: “Oh, so my husband is… he must be that werewolf.”</p>
    <p>During the transformation, the person “jumps three times and takes the form of a dog,” and then “jumps three times and takes the form of a man,” Valentín Suárez recounted. He had the opportunity to observe a werewolf who “lived in a small hut nearby. As soon as the sun was rising, we saw him coming as a dog. It seems he had gone far away and then returned. He arrived as a dog, and we saw him performing somersaults on the ground and transforming into a man.”</p>
    <p>In its animal phase, the <italic>Qom</italic> describe the werewolf as a huge dog with red eyes. It is usually black, but it can also be white. As Valentín Suárez explained: “The color of the werewolf matches the clothes of the person. For example, if the person ties a white scarf around his neck, the werewolf has that white fur collar.” Vilo Viejo added: “The werewolf says [he] doesn’t eat anything beautiful, but [he] eats things that anyone can find in the field, then the werewolf eats, that’s why he’s not fat, thi:::n<fn id="fn5"><label>6</label><p> We use this notation to mark vocalic lengthening that indicates emphasis. Based on her study of the Qom language, Messineo proposes that: “vocalic lengthening is frequently used with expressive intentions, to indicate emphasis, exhortation, surprise, exclamation, interrogation, or any other characteristic of the communicational context” (MESSINEO, 2003, p. 56).</p></fn>, because he eats the things from the field. Anything he can find, sometimes spoiled things, and [he] barely eats beautiful things.” In its animal phase, the man-dog primarily feeds on rotting substances, such as animal corpses found while wandering at night, and also “eats hen dung. That is the ugliest thing. That is what he eats; his food is not beautiful,” explained Félix Suárez.</p>
    <p>Only a few people associate the dog’s nocturnal wanderings with the full moon, Tuesdays, or Fridays. Most assume that the werewolf transforms every night. They also note that dogs “don’t bark but howl” in response to the werewolf. However, dogs usually detect the werewolf only after he has passed: “They cried, but he had already passed by.” In its animal phase, the werewolf can travel long distances. Some say it can walk seven leagues there and seven leagues back, which in Argentina equals approximately 70 kilometers in total. A werewolf told Félix Suárez that he could walk 120 kilometers per hour, giving him a clear advantage when returning home from work as a harvester or traveling to share news. As Félix recounted:</p>
    <p>A brother killed his sibling, and we didn’t know anything because we are far away [from Riacho]. The next day, when he woke up [my aunt’s husband, the werewolf] […], because he had slept      since dawn, because he had      just arrived [to] his settlement, then he slept     . He wakes up at 9am, on a Sunday. […] And I was going to talk to him, and he has recently woken up, he says that in Bartolomé someone has been killed. I didn’t believe him and the ma’am: ‘maybe it did happen [she said]’. The announcement arrived in the afternoon, the police came, [someone] had been killed. He [the werewolf] brought the news first, himself brought the announcement because he saw (<italic>literal translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>Although the werewolf does not attack people in its canine phase, it nonetheless provokes a range of emotions. Some people do not fear it, explaining that “he is a person; once he is formed, he does nothing.” Others, by contrast, panic when they hear dogs howling desperately after the werewolf has passed by. In this context, Mauricio Maidana recounted the following event to me:</p>
    <p>One of our relatives is looking after that field, he says the owner gave him a room, in a big house, a beautiful house […]. And he says that every morning he loses a chunk of meat, when he always wants to prepare some food, the meat is gone: what is going on? […] He says that [one night] he heard the door opened, […] he says he saw something like a shadow, like this, it looks like a person [who] slowly took some meat from the fridge, […] and the man also stood up to see what it was, and when he saw; he saw that [the person] jumped over the clean wiring,he didn’t touch the roof but there was a very light full moon, the whole field was clear, and there, outside, one could see everything, something like a tall calf but it was a dog, and then the fear starts, all night long he doesn’t want to sleep, that’s the real werewolf. And the owner of the house arrived at noon, he is telling me that the man got scared, he doesn’t want to work here anymore, pay me and I’ll be out of here, I’m scared of the animal that came into [the house] (<italic>literal translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>Despite the narrative transcribed above, the fear inspired by the werewolf is closely linked to the ways in which this transformative capacity is acquired. According to what I learned during fieldwork, a person can become a werewolf through two main processes. The first —and most common— involves the invasion of the human body by the <italic>nqui’i</italic> (soul/spirit)<fn id="fn6"><label>7</label><p> <italic>Nqui’i </italic>can be translated as “soul”; lqui’i as “its soul.” For the third person, this lexeme takes the l- (its) mark, indicating inalienability, as occurs for all body parts, internal and external. On this topic, see Messineo (2003). Although historically translated as soul or spirit in the Chaquenean literature, it better corresponds to the notion of <italic>interiority</italic>, as defined by Descola: “a range of properties recognized by all human beings and partially covering what we generally call the mind, the soul, or consciousness: intentionality, subjectivity, reflexivity, feelings, and the ability to express oneself and to dream. It may also include immaterial principles assumed to cause things to be animate, such as breath and vital energy” (DESCOLA, 2013, p. 116). This notion operates together with <italic>physicality</italic>, understood as “a set of visible and tangible expressions of the dispositions peculiar to a particular entity when those dispositions are reputed to result from morphological and physiological characteristics that are intrinsic to it” (DESCOLA, 2013, p. 116).</p></fn> of a dog. Even while in its animal phase, the werewolf can transfer this “spirit” to another person. When this occurs, the first individual loses the ability to transform, while the second acquires it. As people in El Desaguadero explained to me, “the werewolf does not attack people, except when he wants to live. Then he passes between your legs and leaves you his soul, and [then] you are a werewolf.” For this reason, the <italic>Qom</italic> fear the werewolf, since “it is not good to receive the power of the werewolf” (Félix Suárez). People must therefore move carefully at night to prevent the dog from running between their legs and “giving” them this capacity to transform, an issue I discuss in greater detail later.</p>
    <p>A second way of becoming a werewolf is linked to the more general processes through which non-humans relinquish powers to human beings. As Valentín Suárez recounted:</p>
    <p>Once, we went harvesting, four people, (…) one of our comrades was dreaming, sleeping badly for three nights in the tiny space where we slept, and on the fourth day he said: ‘let’s go’. He was sleeping badly because he says the werewolf appeared every night. He says it was the boss who arrived and transformed into a werewolf and offered to give him the power, and he didn’t want to accept it, but he stood at his feet, where he had the mosquito net, and talked to him already turned into a werewolf, he offered the power. And then on the fourth day he said: let’s go! And we harvested until noon and then we went out, we left (<italic>literal translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>Throughout my fieldwork, I frequently observed how non-humans “reach” people at night to discuss the possibility of transferring power. To illustrate, I quote the words of Evaristo Alegre, who describes one of the non-human beings that inhabit the bush:</p>
    <p>They (…), when they want to give you a spirit, to become a doctor, a healer, they show themselves up, they get in your way, they talk to you. (…); if you do not accept, they get to you at night. They get to you, they talk to you, even though your house is well closed, but they reach you, they talk to you (<italic>literal translation</italic>). </p>
    <p>As we have seen, this mode of acquiring the ability to transform into a werewolf integrates the being into <italic>Qom</italic> sociocosmology—which I will discuss in more detail later—without any contradiction. In this way, the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf becomes just another entity within the multitude of beings that inhabit this more-than-human universe.</p>
    <p>However, if the werewolf attribute can be contracted —much like a disease— it can also be cured. Valentín Suárez explained, referring to someone from Riacho de Oro: “That one was a werewolf, but then he left for the lot [<italic>Qom</italic> neighborhood] and he was cured.” Regarding another werewolf who recovered, Vilo Viejo recounted: “There, people told me that you go with, you go around with that [the werewolf], then he is going to pass on the disease he had, and then he was cured. He was cured [the werewolf] and you have to catch that.” The cure can occur not only when the werewolf passes between someone else’s legs, transferring his power as <italic>nqui’i</italic>, but also when a <italic>pi’oxonaq</italic> (shaman) intervenes, as typically happens when a non-human or animal interiority invades the interiority of another person.</p>
    <p>Finally, the werewolf also dies, usually in a more or less “natural” way. <fn id="fn7"><label>8</label><p> I put “natural” in quotation marks because the <italic>Qom </italic>would hardly associate death with a natural cause. On the contrary, they link it to the actions of another human or non-human being.</p></fn> Some people maintain that to kill a werewolf, a white glass bottle must be used, as it is the only effective weapon; others argue that a mere bullet suffices. Nonetheless, when a werewolf dies of old age, he may attempt to persuade a relative to accept the power transfer, much like occurs when a <italic>pi’oxonaq</italic> is near death. All the information presented above raises a central question: Who or what is the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf? To address this, I will briefly review the sociocosmological scenario that may shed light on this question.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>3.Becoming who, becoming what?</bold>
    </p>
    <p>In previous studies on <italic>Qom</italic> zoology (MEDRANO, 2013, 2014), I have focused on demonstrating the continuities between humans and animals. Specifically, this analogy of interiority implies that every being shares similar <italic>lqui’i</italic>, which enables communication, meaning-making, reflexivity, intentionality, and the capacity for deliberate action. Consequently, the differences between humans, animals, and non-humans may be determined by bodily regimes<fn id="fn8"><label>9</label><p> The set of patterns of behavior, appearance, and physical practices through which a being’s bodily capacities, dispositions, and interactions with others are expressed and regulated. Bodily regimes encompass not only external morphological traits but also the ways in which beings establish relationships, engage in social and sexual practices, and participate in shared forms of daily life, thereby marking differences and continuities between humans and non-human entities.</p></fn>, which are manifested not only in external physical forms but also in choices of social and sexual partners. In other words, deciding with whom to be intimate, eat, and live is a key marker of diversity.</p>
    <p>Such bodily regimes have allowed me to conceptualize groups in a relational and non-restrictive way (MEDRANO, 2019), which proves useful for rethinking the human-animal link. On the one hand, <italic>shiỹaxaua</italic> (people) engage in sexual relations and reproduce primarily with other <italic>shiỹaxaua</italic>, consume vegetables and animals considered ‘clean’ or ‘healthy,’ and inhabit domestic spaces. On the other hand, animals tend to reproduce with other animals, consume vegetables and animals that are only occasionally considered clean, and live in the bush, the lake, or the river. A third group can be identified as non-humans: beings endowed with great transformational power and excessive physicalities, capable of causing illness or ontologically preying on humans. A fourth group consists of non-animals, which, while possessing bodily regimes distinct from those typical of animals, hold significant metamorphic power and inhabit the <italic>Qom</italic> sociocosmology, residing in water, on terra firme (solid ground), or in the sky (MEDRANO, 2016).</p>
    <p>The werewolf occupies a liminal space among these groups. It shares characteristics with humans, animals, and non-human beings, moving across boundaries and participating in multiple spheres without fully belonging to any single one. This liminality enables the werewolf to transmit powers, interact with non-humans, and influence social and ecological life in ways inaccessible to ordinary beings. Understanding the werewolf, therefore, requires attention not only to its individual traits but also to the relational and spatial dynamics that define its ambiguous position within the <italic>Qom</italic> sociocosmology, as will be analyzed below.</p>
    <p>What, then, is the place of the werewolf within this schema? Local narratives consistently frame the werewolf as a condition that is acquired rather than inherited. As Valentín Suárez explains, “werewolf, I do not think is going to be the seventh son but anyone because it is a pact.” This statement foregrounds the idea of a voluntary or negotiated process. The werewolf emerges through agreement rather than lineage. Mauricio Maidana offers a complementary account. He states that “the werewolf is not a real dog, otherwise, that dog comes from there, from a grave.” He further explains that “that is the werewolf story, it is not an animal but a ghost.” In this version, the werewolf is understood as a spectral entity. Maidana adds that “sometimes [he] goes into a person and infects him with everything.” Possession and transmission are thus central elements of this narrative. A similar logic appears in the account provided by Vilo Viejo. He explains that “when the werewolf comes out, he does not always come out, but when he does, he is already transformed into a dog, and then he leaves.” Transformation precedes visibility. Félix Suárez reinforces this idea by stating that “this one wasn’t born like that.” He adds that “when he just took that power, he had that spirit.” The power is acquired and embodied. According to Félix Suárez, encounters occur at night: “when you go down the road at night, they say that dog wants to hand the power over to you.” Transmission is attempted through proximity, as “it is a dog, so you do not let him enter your feet” (<italic>our emphasis</italic>).</p>
    <p>Person, spirit or ghost (<italic>nqui’i</italic>), dog, or not-dog. The werewolf occupies an unstable position among these categories. What I emphasize here is that the werewolf embodies a transformation of the human bodily regime through the penetration of an alternative interiority. The <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf could be classified as a “person.” As shown above, he lives among people. He is embedded in a community and a kin network. He speaks, dresses, and behaves in human ways, at least during the daytime. He harvests and remains attentive to community news. At the same time, the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf can be recognized as non-human. He “shows up at night” to give power. He is also contagious, a capacity examined in the following section. The werewolf may also be placed within the category of animals. As <italic>Qom</italic> accounts state, he is a dog. As such, he eats spoiled meat or whatever he finds. Yet the werewolf also exceeds the category of animal. Although he presents an animal corporeality, he displays excessive abilities. He can run long distances. He cannot be perceived by domestic dogs. These capacities situate him within the domain of the non-animal.</p>
    <p>Let me draw several reflections from the foregoing. First, as demonstrated by Tola (2005), having a body is not a <italic>sine qua non</italic> condition for human existence. There are human beings without bodies. The werewolf exemplifies this condition. Lacking a fixed body, he changes, adopts, and wears multiple corporalities. These allow him to establish relationships, experience emotions, and carry out actions. Second, the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf fits all and none of the categories of beings. He thus attests to an ontological instability. This instability takes the form of a permanent imbalance. It remains latent in a context where the boundaries between humans, non-humans, animals, and non-animals are fully permeable. In this setting, the possibility of becoming another constitutes the core of <italic>Qom</italic> sociocosmology.</p>
    <p>Finally, the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf provides a privileged analytical site from which to reaffirm that the categories mentioned above are not given <italic>a priori</italic>. Following Viveiros de Castro (2006, p. 326), they function as “imagination devices.” Operating through the body, these devices emerge in relational contexts and are constantly reshaped through transformation. As Mauricio Maidana explains, “and if you run into [the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf], he goes into the person and infects him with everything, because that animal is inside.” In the following section, I explore the relationship between transformation, the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf, and his capacity for contagion. I suggest that this dynamic constitutes a key site for bringing werewolves and <italic>Qom</italic> cosmology into analytical conversation.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>4.To become infected with the </bold>
      <bold>
        <italic>Qom</italic>
      </bold>
      <bold> werewolf</bold>
    </p>
    <p>At this point, it becomes clear that <italic>Qom</italic> sociocosmology is structured by transformation. Human beings do not simply <italic>are</italic>; they become. A person’s body and <italic>nqui’i</italic> are shaped from a very early age, even before birth. This process unfolds through parental actions and through contact with other beings (cf. TOLA, 2005). Relations with animals are central to this process. Animals provide many of the qualities that humans seek to incorporate. Animality thus participates in the construction of humanity. Yet the inverse process is also possible. Beings that belong to the <italic>fauna </italic>may impose certain features on humans without their consent. Such encounters can result in pathogenic conditions (MEDRANO, 2013).</p>
    <p>Such situations have been examined within the framework of what <italic>Qom</italic> people call <italic>nauoga</italic>, a notion commonly translated as “contagion.” Tola defines <italic>nauoga</italic> as the process through which formal or behavioral characteristics are transmitted between the <italic>nqui’i</italic> of human and non-human beings at specific moments of the life cycle (TOLA, 2005). Other authors<fn id="fn9"><label>10</label><p> For classic works on the nauoga process, see Karsten (1932) and Métraux (1996[1946]); for contemporary approaches, see Vuoto (1981), Balducci (1982), Idoyaga Molina (2005), Wright (2008), and Medrano (2013).</p></fn> have explored how this notion of contagion operates within <italic>Qom</italic> conceptions of disease. Below, I summarize several examples to illustrate the scope of this phenomenon and to analyze situations in which one may ‘come down with the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf’.</p>
    <p>First, it is important to recall that the <italic>Qom</italic> body is conceived “more as a concrete space of interaction and metamorphosis than as a ‘natural’ condition that preexists intersubjective or ‘intercorporeal’ relations” (TOLA, 2005, p. 127). For these Indigenous people, the collective space is where a person is formed and transformed. This understanding gives rise to the notion of a “multiple person, [which] is manifested in the process of becoming when adopting diverse bodily regimes” (TOLA, 2005, p. 127). Bodies are considered especially vulnerable to transformation during pregnancy and the first months of life. On this point, Métraux (1996[1946]) notes that “when a woman knows she is pregnant, both she and her husband refrain from foods and activities that could endanger the birth or harm the child’s appearance or character” (p. 178, <italic>our emphasis</italic>). In this regard, Mauricio Maidana offered me the following advice:</p>
    <p>Pregnant women must be careful when looking at the <italic>huoỹem</italic>’s face [howler monkey], feed it or hit it, because it will be contagious to the baby. He can be born with the animal’s face or with its expressions and movements, when adults talk to him [to the human baby], he does not understand and just smiles [like the monkey does] (Mauricio Maidana in MEDRANO; MAIDANA; GÓMEZ, 2011, p. 70, <italic>our translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>Following the words of V. S. Sosa, a <italic>Qom</italic> man, as transcribed by Luis Vuoto (1981, p. 104), “a pregnant woman cannot eat surubí [<italic>Pseudoplatystoma </italic>spp.]<italic>” </italic>because it would be contagious for the baby. People <italic>“</italic>used to eat it [the surubí fish], thus infecting the child, who has no hair… he was bald at birth, he won’t have any hair until he has grown up” (VUOTO, 1981, p. 104, <italic>our translation</italic>). The child becomes bald, like the skin of the surubí. The same narrator explains that if a fox bites a piece of meat abandoned by a hunter, and that meat is later given to a pregnant woman, “the child is born very thin” (VUOTO, 1981, p. 106). Only a shaman can cure this condition. As V. S. Sosa recounts, “every time he [the shaman] sang he sucked, and extracted the fox’s skin first, and then the spine, the tiny bones (…). After the whole fox is out, [the person] heals” (VUOTO, 1981, p. 107). All these cases involve contagion. The <italic>nqui’i</italic>, or interiority, of injured or damaged animals is transferred to children. As a result, children look or behave in ways that are not fully human. This pathological state is rooted in the potentiality of bodily multiplicity. Healing occurs only when a <italic>pi’oxonaq</italic> separates the blended interiorities, thereby restoring distinction.</p>
    <p>The contagious nature of the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf must be understood within this conception of the body-person. Bodies become in an environment where ontological boundaries between beings are weak. This framework allows bodily regimes to be exchanged, combined, or altered. Interiority, however, remains relational rather than fixed. It does not express a predetermined group affiliation but a capacity for connection. This helps explain why the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf —perhaps a wandering interiority in search of a body— is contagious. He can be transmitted and cured. In doing so, he crosses ontological boundaries and becomes a warning about the porous limits between humanity and animality.</p>
    <p>Returning to <italic>Qom</italic> ideas about the distinction between humans and animals, humans are those who eat and engage in sexual relations as humans. Animals, by contrast, adopt alternative modes of being that are clearly non-human. Peter Gow’s work (1989) among Indigenous peoples of the Lower Urubamba River in Peru resonates with these concerns. By examining food and sexual desire, Gow introduces the figure of the “perverse child” (GOW, 1989, p. 578). Perverse children eat dirt, a substance considered non-food within a subsistence economy that <italic>“</italic>works because only certain forms of sexual and oral desire are legitimate, and the desire to eat earth is not one of them<italic>”</italic> (GOW, 1989, p. 579).</p>
    <p>Food and sexuality are thus embedded in a dense network of desires that structures social life. They are a central concern in Indigenous worlds. The “perverse child’s horrifying project is to build a world in which its desires matter only to itself”(GOW, 1989, p. 581). In the <italic>Qom</italic> case, although the werewolf oscillates between human and animal forms, he clearly abandons both human food practices and sexual relations with his equals. He thus becomes a liminal project of humanity, positioned on an edge too blurred to allow full incorporation into the human domain.</p>
    <p>For the Gran Chaco region, Anatilde Idoyaga Molina provides perhaps the only ethnographic reference to werewolves among other Indigenous groups.<fn id="fn10"><label>11</label><p> In 2013, Sarra also commented on the presence of werewolves in a Qom suburban neighborhood. She mentions that such beings “are part of the beings we can classify as non-humans of ‘other races’ than human” (SARRA, 2013, p. 69, <italic>our translation</italic>).</p></fn> She states that, for the Pilagá people, “the mechanism through which a person becomes a werewolf is identical to any process entailing the acquisition of a certain status or specific power, according to the traditional worldvision<italic>” </italic>(IDOYAGA MOLINA, 1986, p. 229, <italic>our translation</italic>). This formulation situates the werewolf within broader Indigenous logics of power acquisition rather than as an exceptional or marginal figure. The <italic>payák</italic>-werewolf exemplifies how the attributes associated with this being are reworked within the Pilagá sociocultural framework. As Idoyaga Molina notes, this configuration admits processes of syncretism. These include, for instance, the incorporation of Christian calendar days as appropriate moments for transformation. Such adaptations do not dissolve Indigenous ontologies but rearticulate them in historically situated ways. For this reason, Idoyaga Molina concludes that it is misleading to treat Creole and Pilagá werewolves as a unified figure (IDOYAGA MOLINA, 1986, p. 235). Each emerges from a distinct relational world. Each responds to specific ontological premises. Taking this insight seriously prevents the flattening of difference and foregrounds the plurality of cosmological arrangements in which the werewolf operates.</p>
    <p>Inspired by this ethnographic intervention, and starting from a sketch of the non-Indigenous werewolf, the following section undertakes a final analytical exercise. It places different werewolves in dialogue with their respective worlds, not to compare them as variants of a single figure, but to explore how each articulates particular regimes of transformation, power, and becoming.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>5.To be born a Creole werewolf</bold>
    </p>
    <p>Although the werewolf has been examined from multiple perspectives, folkloric approaches remain the most common. These studies tend to frame the werewolf as a myth or legend. In doing so, they deny the immanent character that this figure holds within <italic>Qom</italic> sociocosmology.<fn id="fn11"><label>12</label><p> For example, Acosta, who collects stories about non-humans in Guaraní cosmology, published his outreach work under the title “Guaraní Mythology.” He mentions that “since pre-Columbian times, Guaraní people already believed in the ‘Yaguareté-avá’ (man-tiger) transformation” (ACOSTA, 2015, p. 21, <italic>our emphasis, our translation</italic>), thereby relegating the werewolf to the sphere of belief and denying it full existence.</p></fn> To account for transformations of men into wolves in modern contexts, folkloric studies often echo descriptions found in ancient sources. Romano (1997, p. 76), for example, notes that in <italic>Naturalis historia</italic> (published in 77 CE), Pliny the Elder had already narrated the case of “Anto,” who, after violating a religious prohibition, was taken to a place where he transformed into a wolf for nine months. According to the literature, the origin of the werewolf figure is often located in the Scandinavian–Teutonic area.<fn id="fn12"><label>13</label><p> In this regard, Ginzburg (2013) made one of the most interesting contributions. He describes the doings of the Benandanti (“Good Walkers”), a widespread sect in Friuli, Italy, during the 16th and 17th centuries. By reconstructing the past based on Inquisition documents, he narrates a trial in Livonia against an “old man wolf.” This elder, named Thiess, told the judges that three times a year he goes, together with other men-wolf, to “the end of the sea” to fight witches and sorcerers for the crops’ fertility (GINZBURG, 2013, pp. 256–257, <italic>our translation</italic>). These “beliefs of <italic>shamanic </italic>backgrounds” (GINZBURG, 2013, p. 264, <italic>our translation</italic>), linked by Ginzburg to mythology, were scattered across Europe and clearly related to fertility and pilgrimages of the deceased.</p></fn> From there, it appears in the English-speaking world and later travels to the New World aboard Portuguese ships. It spreads widely and eventually reaches the River Plate region (GRANADA, 1959; ROMANO, 1997).</p>
    <p>Romano (1997, p. 77) observes that wolf mutation, known as lycanthropy, was documented in antiquity but intensified during the Middle Ages. When the figure arrived on the Argentine coast —where wolves were absent— it became embodied in other animals, such as the <italic>aguará guazú</italic>. This displacement, as noted earlier, produced the equivocation that motivates this paper. In Ambrosetti’s (1967) compendium of superstitions and legends (ROMANO, 1997, pp. 99-100), the werewolf appears only briefly. It is in the work of Félix Coluccio, however, that a detailed description emerges, still grounded in a myth-based folkloric perspective. Coluccio traces the changing features of the werewolf across time and space, following different Ibero-American contexts. <italic>“</italic>According to widespread belief<italic>,” he writes, “</italic>the werewolf is the seventh male son of a family<italic>” </italic>(COLUCCIO, 1992, p. 54, <italic>our translation, our emphasis</italic>).</p>
    <p>Described as a mixture of dog and pig, this werewolf wanders every Tuesday and Friday at midnight. He reveals his monstrous form. He feeds on scraps and unbaptized children. He seeks to <italic>“</italic>exterminate by all means <bold>whoever</bold> frees him from his curse<italic>”</italic> (COLUCCIO, 1992, p. 54, <italic>our translation</italic>). In a similar vein, Daniel Granada writes: <italic>“</italic>At night and during certain hours, the man destined for such fate goes unavoidably to the places where he will be transformed into any quadrupedal he can find, then charging against passers-by. By making him pour blood, he regains his initial form. The last child of a series of seven consecutive sons is the <italic>lobishómen</italic>” (GRANADA, 1959, pp. 402–403, <italic>our translation</italic>). </p>
    <p>In short, this werewolf —the seventh son, violent and bloodthirsty— has become the most widespread figure. He has inspired countless literary, cinematic, and visual productions, as well as a rich body of oral narratives across Latin America. However, when the topic is approached beyond folklore, other werewolves emerge. These figures resonate more closely with what the <italic>Qom</italic> describe. Blache’s structural analysis of the werewolf among Paraguayan migrants in Buenos Aires offers one such example. She summarizes the figure as follows: <italic>“</italic>he turns into a dog on Fridays at night. (…) As a dog, he goes to the cemetery, where he feeds on corpses. Then, he turns back into a man, and goes back to his house. As a person, he is distinguished by his physical appearance: he is thin, pale, and has a sickly look. His behavior is that of a hardly sociable person who avoids other people’s company”(BLACHE, 1972-78, p. 23, <italic>our translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>Likewise, Vidal de Battini, a teacher, essayist, and researcher, published the werewolf narratives she collected in the Northeast and Northwest of Argentina. While many of these accounts reproduce a conventional mythic image of the werewolf, others situate him within everyday life. She records, for example: “it says / it is said that a ma’am was married to a werewolf. (…) they took him prisoner and she went with her family” (VIDAL DE BATTINI, 1984, p. 541, <italic>our translation</italic>); “InItuzaingó, near the Iberá lagoon, there was a ma’am who had a husband who was a werewolf. She had a sick child. (…) All night long the husband was gone” (1984, p. 552); “When an animal, he does no harm. He eats little bones (…). The other dogs don’t do anything to him<italic>” </italic>(1984, p. 557); and finally,<italic> “</italic>He can be cured by means of a healer, any payé” (1984, p. 572). As these examples suggest, even in Creole and rural contexts where a person is said to be born a werewolf, his presence oscillates between two registers. One situates him in a purified mythical domain. The other places him within the everyday lives of people.</p>
    <p>The <italic>Qom</italic> themselves recognize the existence of non-Indigenous werewolves. They mention werewolves from Corrientes Province, Paraguayan werewolves, Pilagá <italic>le’c</italic> werewolves, and <italic>Qom</italic> werewolves. This multiplicity disrupts key assumptions of so-called naturalist societies (<italic>sensu</italic> DESCOLA). In such frameworks, humanity and animality are discontinuous. Human bodies, folded in on themselves, form sealed compartments that isolate the self once and for all. In this context, the werewolf appears as a boundary figure that unsettles these rationalities. By transforming <bold>humans</bold> into animal corporealities, he mocks the purifying operations that separate nature from culture, animal from human, and excess from reason.</p>
    <p>The materials discussed so far show that the werewolf cannot be reduced to a single figure or explanatory model. Rather than a myth, the werewolf appears as a relational being shaped by specific sociocosmological contexts. <italic>Qom</italic>, Pilagá, Creole, and other Indigenous werewolves articulate different regimes of transformation, corporeality, and power. These variations indicate that what is at stake is not a shared narrative but distinct ontological arrangements. The werewolf thus functions less as a stable character than as a problem-space through which boundaries between humanity, animality, and otherness are negotiated. To make these differences explicit, the following section places the various werewolves discussed here in comparative perspective, highlighting their modes of becoming, bodily regimes, sources of power, and relational effects.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>6.Werewolves in dialogue</bold>
    </p>
    <p>Lastly, in the following table (<bold>Table 1</bold>) I compare the ‘werewolf myth’ —who appears not only in Creole and rural scenarios (cf. ANCONATANI, 2022) but also in urban contexts— with the ‘<italic>Qom</italic>-werewolf’, of whom you have already read enough throughout this article. The aim is to bring into conversation ideas of humanity and animality that both beings make visible.</p>
    <p><bold>Table 1 </bold>– Comparative table of the werewolf in the Creole–rural–urban world and the Indigenous <italic>Qom </italic>world</p>
    <table-wrap id="tbl1">
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="center">Werewolf-myth</td>
            <td align="center">
              <italic>Qom</italic>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">The werewolf is born (congenital failure): the seventh son.</td>
            <td align="left">The werewolf becomes; he transforms (ontological alteration).</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">May attack humans.</td>
            <td align="left">By taking precautions, he is not a threat to humans.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Cannot be cured. </td>
            <td align="left">Can be cured by separating the </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Transforms on full-moon nights or on Tuesday and Friday nights.</td>
            <td align="left">Transforms every night.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Has no positive characteristics. </td>
            <td align="left">One positive aspect: his speed.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Is not a myth but the introduction of a non-human—an animal or a non-animal—into a human group.</td>
            <td align="left">Is a myth, a legend, but also the introduction of a non-human, </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Is the limit of humanity, due to his bestial and asocial character.</td>
            <td align="left">Is both an intermediary between humanity and animality and a limit of the former. </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <p>Source: author’s own elaboration, 2024.</p>
    <p>As previously discussed, the <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf can be understood as the expression of a transformational potentiality that, when activated within the Indigenous world, gives form to human–animal becomings. This potentiality constitutes the cornerstone of a sociocosmology in which the distinction between those who compose humanity and those who compose animality is one of degree rather than kind. From this perspective, a question emerges: could the werewolf myth represent the expression of an opposing logic? Might it constitute a loose end —an unresolved remainder with which modernity and its so-called process of purification have never fully come to terms? Could it be read, <italic>à la</italic> Latour, as evidence that we have never been entirely modern?</p>
    <p>Within his schema of the four ontologies, Descola argues that “naturalism is the mirror opposite of animism and characterizes the modern world and Western thought” (DESCOLA, 2010, p. 33). As the author suggests, this naturalistic ontological arrangement is grounded in a differentiation of interiority between humans and non-humans —and, we may add, between humans and animals— while presupposing a continuity at the level of physicality:</p>
    <p>[…] humans alone are supposed to have a meaningful selfhood whether individual (mind, capacity for symbolism) or collective (<italic>Volksgeist</italic>, cultures). In contrast, clearly since Descartes, and more neatly even since Darwin, humans and non-humans are linked by their shared physicality: they belong to a continuum where the same laws of physics, biology and chemistry apply (DESCOLA, 2010, p. 338). </p>
    <p>We contend that these ontological equations describe the general processes through which continuities and discontinuities between humans and non-humans emerge within a given society (DESCOLA, 2016, p. 149). However, such conceptual systems are not exempt from fissures. Through these fissures, several beings —such as werewolves— can emerge. Werewolves operate by dodging worlds and symmetrizing cosmologies. They function as an ‘antidote to incommensurability’<fn id="fn13"><label>14</label><p> With this expression, we refer to the existence of a vitality —in this case, the werewolf— which partially makes intelligible the incommensurable difference established between different ontologies (for example, the modern and the animistic). The <italic>lobizón</italic>, in the case presented, circumstantially brings into dialogue two cosmological scenarios that are otherwise disjointed.</p></fn>. This enables specific local understandings. This is particularly relevant in the disproportionately uneven and violent contexts where relations between Indigenous and Creole people, peasants, and ‘village people’ are immersed, particularly in the Argentine Northeast.</p>
    <p>While the werewolf-myth (Creole/urban) functions as a residue of congenital failure —a figure confirming the naturalistic discontinuity of interiorities (Descola)— the <italic>Qom</italic>-werewolf embodies an ontological transformation, demonstrating fluidity. However, the comparative analysis between the Werewolf-myth and the <italic>Qom</italic>-Werewolf reveals the precise mechanisms by which distinct cosmologies define the boundary between the human and the animal. We contend that the persistence of these divergent werewolf forms constitutes a fissure in modernity, challenging the purification project described by Latour. Placing these figures in dialogue thus allows us to move beyond mere comparison, forcing a confrontation with the limits of Western categories and opening up an anthropological project concerned with the multiplication of worlds.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>7.Final considerations</bold>
    </p>
    <p>When I initially began investigating the werewolf, I feared the topic would not be of interest to the <italic>Qom</italic> community. I even felt I was encroaching upon a subject ‘better left unspoken’. However, one morning in March 2018 in Riacho de Oro, I worked through the discomfort —the shame of someone who persistently asks about a sensitive matter. It was then that Félix Suárez clarified the issue for me:</p>
    <p>This is why all of that has to be known, because without knowing that, one might like making [becoming a] werewolf. But beyond [that, it is] uglier. Because when you turn into another kind it is not pretty, a malevolent spirit of the world travels. I say, no matter how poor one may be, has nothing, but let one be just a man. You have to be a man, a person, a healthy person, who does not transform into anything (<italic>literal translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>Félix’s words prompted this discussion and provided a justification for the subsequent werewolf analysis. These accounts, though not entirely settled, compel reflection on the notions of humanity and animality emerging in both Indigenous and non-Indigenous worlds. The <italic>Qom</italic> werewolf transformation, in summary, responds to a conception of the body/person as a process of becoming within a specific environment. We have demonstrated that the ontological boundaries separating beings —humans, non-humans, animals, and non-animals— are weak in this context. This weakness allows the bodily regime to metamorphose. Crucially, the transformation remains anchored in an interiority that does not express affiliation with a specific group. Rather, it expresses belonging to a sociocosmology we label animistic. This contrasts with societies currently labeled as naturalistic. Yet, the werewolf appears to be the limit case that challenges Western rationalities. Sometimes treated as a legend or myth —non-existent phenomena— it persists in appearing and disappearing, thus embodying the logic of ontological purification.</p>
    <p>Beyond the historical studies on the werewolf, we also consider works aligned with ethnohistory, such as those by Podruchny (2004), Harris (2008), and Ginzburg (2013). Podruchny, specifically, analyzes the tales of a nineteenth-century explorer in Canadian Algonquian territories. She links the werewolf figure to the Wendigo—beings that, within Indigenous cosmology, possess cannibalistic capabilities. Podruchny views these stories as “reminiscent of many instances of cross-cultural exchange” (PODRUCHNY, 2004, p. 694). She concludes that although werewolves and Wendigos “constituted different social phenomena [plural],they were blurred <bold>together</bold> in the northwest as they became a site of cultural conjunction, and they led to the emergence of a new cultural form of métissage” (PODRUCHNY, 2004, p. 694). However, this argument remains problematic. It aligns with a notion of <italic>mestizaje</italic> that relies on “a theory about mixing and social change assumed without major problematizations” (KELLY, 2016, p. 25, <italic>our translation</italic>). This approach fails to account for the power dynamics and epistemic heterogeneities that likely nuanced the relations between Indigenous peoples and travelers at that time.</p>
    <p>Harris (2008) adopts a different perspective. He analyzes 18th-century documents from the public archives of Pará in Belém, Brazil. His work examines the relations between the Portuguese colonizers, various Indigenous groups, and local Brazilians—a population born on Latin American soil. Specifically, Harris analyzes an “edict of justification”. This edict was issued by a prominent figure born in Bahia in 1760: an ex-magistrate, militia captain, slave owner, landlord, and merchant. Crucially, this individual was also accused of being a werewolf. Harris positions the werewolf narrative within a “border of imagination” (HARRIS, 2008, p. 39, <italic>our translation</italic>). He understands imagination as the movement that allows for the acknowledgment of the other in colonial contexts. By linking the werewolf to Indigenous cosmological figures, transformational abilities, and shamanism, this border negotiates the metamorphosis of humans and animals. Harris simultaneously presents the werewolf image as a “conceptual bridge.” This bridge illuminates “a mutual learning of abilities, beliefs, and displaced and transported worldviews, without the existence of an actually harmonious meeting between those patterns” (HARRIS, 2008, p. 54, <italic>our translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>This proposal directly relates to a key argument of this article: considering the werewolf as an antidote to local incommensurability. By fracturing the human-animal boundaries across the cosmologies under discussion, the werewolf introduces transformation as a genuine possibility. This allows ‘others’ to achieve at least partial recognition of themselves. However, as Harris (HARRIS, 2008) argues, encounters between these actors still retain the traditional disproportions inherent in Indigenous and non-Indigenous relations.</p>
    <p>The notion of the “border of imagination” (HARRIS, 2008, ) is echoed when we view the werewolf as an “ontological mocker”. We are referring to the ability of this existing system to integrate the scenarios of diverse ontologies, making its boundaries permeable. Through this capacity, the werewolf disrupts categorical distinctions within <italic>Qom</italic> cosmology. The figure incessantly becomes human, non-human, animal, or non-animal. The werewolf thus reminds us of the perpetual imbalance<fn id="fn14"><label>15</label><p> In relation to the notion of “dualism in perpetual imbalance” outlined by Lévi-Strauss (1992).</p></fn> from which society and its relative order emerge. Furthermore, the werewolf evades cosmological distinctions —animistic, naturalistic, and others— thereby democratizing animal becoming. However, the werewolf is not the sole protagonist of this becoming. In the Amazon basin, we find the pink river dolphin, also known as the <italic>bufeo</italic> or <italic>boto</italic>. These beings reportedly dwell in deep waters and possess various modern technologies. As detailed by Luisa Belaunde (2015, 2018), who builds upon the 1954 writings of folklorist Câmara Cascudo:</p>
    <p>Their bodies are beautiful and seductive. When they surface, they cause an intense passion in the persons who see them, and the desire to follow them to the water depths may take their love victims to drown. Their appearance outside water is the same as that of white men and women, blond hair, elegantly dressed and seductive. They like to dance at pubs, to drink and to charm. The only thing that betrays them is the fish smell they exhale from their heads, and that they try to cover with a hat (BELAUNDE, 2018, p. 109, <italic>our translation</italic>).</p>
    <p>Belaunde (2018) notes that the smell of menstrual blood and subsequent sexual desire trigger the <italic>bufeo’s</italic> transformation into human form. She describes them as “the shamans of love elixirs” (2018, p. 111, <italic>our translation</italic>). In the riverside worlds of Peru and Brazil, these human-animal beings appear to Indigenous women who disregard menstrual reclusion. They offer an irresistible sexual relationship that leads the women to dwell with them in the water depths. <italic>Bufeos</italic> adopt a predatory stance toward women. Yet, they are not destructive; community members highly value their powerful influence over loving powers (BELAUNDE, 2015). Significantly, this human-<italic>bufeo</italic> transformation is also documented among non-Indigenous populations of the Amazon. Deborah de Magalhães Lima (2014), for instance, suggests understanding the ‘bufeo legend’ as a “simplified translation of the narratives that have the history of the Amazon colonization as a background” (LIMA, 2014, p. 2, <italic>our translation</italic>). She argues that, in these historical scenarios of social conjunction, <italic>bufeos</italic> evidence indelible Indigenous cosmologies shaping encounters between different worlds —Indigenous, non-Indigenous, or White.</p>
    <p>Returning to the comparison, both the werewolf and the <italic>bufeo</italic> evade boundaries. The werewolf crosses into Indigenous worlds; the <italic>bufeo</italic> crosses into non-Indigenous ones. Within Amerindian cosmologies, these figures are present. They evidence a key criterion for animality: eating or having sexual relations with humans. Any entity engaging in these acts is deemed animal. They also exist outside these cosmologies. By interlinking the Indigenous and non-Indigenous worlds, these figures challenge the integrity of the latter, which falters in its modernity.</p>
    <p>Finally, the werewolf of the Chaco region is clearly not a singular entity. This figure manifests as a result of an ontogenic alteration in the Creole case or an ontological transformation in the Indigenous case. Thus, we encounter not merely two, but several werewolves. This multiplicity, however, raises a critical question: Does this effectively enable the multiplication of worlds—a necessary requirement for diplomacy—that allows us to initiate a conversation between them? Concurrently, are there as many <italic>bufeos</italic> as there are worlds enacting them? Ultimately, we must heed the words of Viveiros de Castro (2010): “If there is something that <italic>de jure</italic> belongs to anthropology, it is not the task of explaining the world of the other but that of multiplying our world” (VIVEIROS DE CASTRO, 2010, p. 211, <italic>our translation</italic>). For this project, continued dialogue with werewolves, <italic>bufeos</italic>, and countless others remains essential.</p>
    <p>In conclusion, the comparative analysis of these two ontologies —manifested in the distinct forms of the lobizón and the <italic>bufeo</italic>— underscores the heterogeneity of non-human becoming. The figure of the lobizón, poised between ontogenic alteration and ontological transformation, serves as a powerful device to interrogate the purported stability of the human-animal boundary. Furthermore, by placing these figures in dialogue, we move beyond simply documenting differences. Instead, we reveal that transformation itself is the key analytical category, challenging the Western preoccupation with essences. Ultimately, the ontological slippage enacted by beings like the lobizón and the <italic>bufeo </italic>demands an anthropological practice focused not on defining the world, but on recognizing its inherent multiplicity. This comparative method thus provides a necessary starting point for the diplomatic project of putting worlds into conversation.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>8.Acknowledgments</bold>
    </p>
    <p>I thank Lucila Bugallo, Penélope Dransart, and Francisco Pazzarelli for organizing the amazing workshop in Tilcara, where I presented this work for the first time. I also thank Francisco Pazzarelli and Carolina Rivet, who read an early draft of this article and offered very insightful comments. I am grateful to Luisa Elvira Belaunde for her reference to the “perverse child,” and to Thiago da Costa Oliveira for introducing me to Ginzburg’s work. My gratitude goes to the Qom for sharing both werewolves and friendship with me, and to Agustina de Chazal for the passionate translation of this text.</p>
    <p>
      <bold>9.References</bold>
    </p>
    <p>ACOSTA, Ertivio. <bold>Mitología Guaraní</bold>. Resistencia: Instituto de Cultura de la Provincia del Chaco, 2015.</p>
    <p>AMBROSETTI, Juan Bautista. <bold>Supersticiones y leyendas</bold>. Santa Fe: Editorial Castellvi, 1967.</p>
    <p>ANCONATANI, Leonardo Martín. ‘Un perro negro así grandote’. El lobisón criollo entre la historia clásica y los devenires indígenas en el este de Formosa (Argentina). <bold>R@U</bold>, v. 14, n. 1, p. 219-245, 2022. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.52426/rau.v14i1.413">10.52426/rau.v14i1.413</ext-link>. </p>
    <p>BALDUCCI, María Isabel. <bold>Códigos de comunicación con el mundo animal entre los Toba-Taksik</bold>. Director: José Braunstein.1982. 122 f. Tesis (Licenciatura en Antropología). Facultad de Filosofía y Letras, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, 1982.</p>
    <p>BELAUNDE, Luisa Elvira. Resguardo e sexualidade(s): uma antropologia simétrica das sexualidades amazônicas em transformação. <bold>Cadernos de campo</bold>, v. 24, p. 538-564, 2015. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.11606/issn.2316-9133.v24i24p538-564">10.11606/issn.2316-9133.v24i24p538-564</ext-link>. </p>
    <p>BELAUNDE, Luisa Elvira. <bold>Sexualidades amazónicas. Género, deseos y alteridades</bold>. Lima: La Siniestra Ensayos, 2018.</p>
    <p>BLACHE, Martha. Análisis estructural de una creencia de la zona guaranítica: El lobizón. <bold>Cuadernos del Instituto Nacional de Antropología</bold>, v. 8, p. 21-42, 1972-1978.</p>
    <p>COLUCCIO, Félix. <bold>Fauna del terror en el folklore iberoamericano</bold>. Buenos Aires: Editorial Plus Ultra, 1992.</p>
    <p>DESCOLA, Philippe. Cognition, Perception and Worlding. <bold>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</bold>, v.35, n.3-4, p. 334-340, 2010. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1179/030801810X12772143410287">10.1179/030801810X12772143410287</ext-link>. </p>
    <p>DESCOLA, Philippe. <bold>Beyond Nature and Culture</bold><bold><italic>.</italic></bold> Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2013.</p>
    <p>DESCOLA, Philippe.<bold> La composición de los mundos. Conversaciones con Pierre Charbonnier</bold>. Buenos Aires: Capital Intelectual, 2016.</p>
    <p>GINZBURG, Carlo. <bold>Mitos, emblemas e indicios: morfología e historia</bold>. Buenos Aires: Prometeo, 2013.</p>
    <p>GOW, Peter. The Perverse Child: Desire in a Native Amazonian Subsistence Economy. <bold>Man</bold>, v. 24, n. 4, p. 567-582, 1989. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.2307/2804288">10.2307/2804288</ext-link>. </p>
    <p>GRANADA, Daniel. <bold>Reseña histórica-descriptiva de antiguas y modernas supersticiones del Río de la Plata</bold>. Buenos Aires: Guillermo Kraft, 1959.</p>
    <p>HARRIS, Mark. O lobisomem entre índios e brancos: o trabalho da imaginação no Grão-Pará no final do século XVIII. <bold>Revista do Instituto de Estudos Brasileiros</bold>, v. 47, p. 29-55, 2008. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.11606/issn.2316-901X.v0i47p29-55">10.11606/issn.2316-901X.v0i47p29-55</ext-link>.</p>
    <p>IDOYAGA MOLINA, Anatilde. La integración de la figura del lobizón entre los pilagá. <bold>Studi e materiali di Storia delle Religioni</bold>, v. 52, n. X-2, p. 227-236, p. 1986.</p>
    <p>IDOYAGA MOLINA, Anatilde. Reflexiones sobre la clasificación de medicinas. Análisis de una propuesta conceptual. <bold>Scripta Ethnologica</bold>, v. 27, p. 111-147, 2005. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/148115160">148115160</ext-link>. Retrieved on:March27, 2022.</p>
    <p>KARSTEN, Rafael. <bold>Indian tribes of the Argentine and Bolivian Chaco</bold>. Helsingfors: Societas Scientiarum Fennica, 1932.</p>
    <p>KELLY, José Antonio. <bold>Sobre a antimestiçagem</bold>. Florianópolis: Cultura e Barbárie, 2016.</p>
    <p>LÉVI-STRAUSS, Claude. <bold>Historia de Lince</bold>. Anagrama: Barcelona, 1992.</p>
    <p>LIMA, Deborah de Magalhães. O homem branco e o boto: o encontro colonial em narrativas de encantamento e transformação (médio rio Solimões, Amazonas). <bold>Teoria e sociedade, Antropologias e arqueologias hoje</bold>, p. 173-201, 2014.</p>
    <p>MEDRANO, Celeste. Devenir-en-transformación: debates etnozoológicos en torno a la metamorfosis animal entre los qom. <italic>In</italic>: TOLA, Florencia; MEDRANO, Celeste; CARDIN, Lorena (Eds.). <bold>Gran Chaco. Ontología, poder, afectividad</bold>. Buenos Aires: IWGIA/Rumbo Sur, 2013.</p>
    <p>MEDRANO, Celeste. Zoo-sociocosmología <italic>qom</italic>: seres humanos, animales y sus relaciones en el Gran Chaco, <bold>Journal de la Societé des Americanistes</bold>, v. 100 n. 1: 225-257, 2014 DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.4000/jsa.13777">10.4000/jsa.13777</ext-link>. </p>
    <p>MEDRANO, Celeste. Los no-animales y la categoría ‘animal’. Definiendo la zoo-sociocosmología entre los toba (qom) del Chaco argentino. <bold>Mana</bold>, v. 22, n. 2, p. 369-402, 2016. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1590/1678-49442016v22n2p369">10.1590/1678-49442016v22n2p369</ext-link>.</p>
    <p>MEDRANO, Celeste. Taxonomías relacionales o de qué se valen los qom y los animales para clasificarse. <bold>Tabula Rasa</bold>, v. 31, p. 161-183, 2019. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.25058/20112742.n31.07">10.25058/20112742.n31.07</ext-link>. </p>
    <p>MEDRANO, Celeste. Componiendo lobizones. Reflexiones sobre animalidad y humanidad junto a los qom (tobas) del Gran Chaco argentino. <italic>In</italic>: BUGALLO, Lucila; DRANSART, Penélope; PAZZARELLI, Francisco (Eds.). <bold>Animales humanos, </bold><bold>humanos animales</bold><bold>. Relaciones y transformaciones en mundos indígenas sudamericanos</bold>. Buenos Aires: Editorial Antropofagia, 2022.</p>
    <p>MEDRANO, Celeste; Mauricio, MAIDANA; Cirilo, GÓMEZ. <bold>Zoología Qom. Conocimientos tobas sobre el mundo animal</bold>. Santa Fe: Ediciones Biológica, 2011.</p>
    <p>MESSINEO, Cristina. <bold>Lengua Toba (guaycuru). Aspectos gramaticales y discursivos</bold>. Alemania: Lincom Europa Academic Publisher, 48, 2003.</p>
    <p>MÉTRAUX, Alfred. <bold>Etnografía del Chaco</bold>. Paraguay: El Lector, 1996 [1946].</p>
    <p>PODRUCHNY, Carolyn. Werewolves and windigos: narratives of cannibal monsters in French-Canadian voyageur oral tradition. <bold>Ethnohistory</bold>, v. 51, n. 4, p. 677-700, 2004. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1215/00141801-51-4-677">10.1215/00141801-51-4-677</ext-link>. </p>
    <p>ROMANO, Eduardo. La emigración de los lobizones del imaginario popular a La industria cultural. <bold>Revista de Investigaciones Folklóricas</bold>, v. 12, p. 76-85, 1997.</p>
    <p>SARRA, Sonia Elizabeth. Lobizón, pomberos y duendes. Continuidades y transformaciones en un contexto urbano desde la mirada de los niños qom. <bold>Kula, Antropólogos del Atlántico Sur</bold>, v. 8, p. 65-78, 2013.</p>
    <p>TOLA, Florencia. Personas corporizadas, multiplicidades y extensiones: un acercamiento a las nociones de cuerpo y persona entre los tobas (qom) del Chaco argentino. <bold>Revista Colombiana de Antropología</bold>, v. 41, p. 107-134, 2005. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.22380/2539472X.1204">10.22380/2539472X.1204</ext-link>.</p>
    <p>VIDAL DE BATTINI, Berta Elena. <bold>Cuentos y leyendas populares de la Argentina. </bold>Tomo VIII. Buenos Aires: Argentina, Ediciones Culturales Argentinas, Ministerio de Educación y Justicia, Secretaría de Cultura, 1984.</p>
    <p>VIVEIROS DE CASTRO, Eduardo, A floresta de cristal: notas sobre a ontologia dos espíritos amazônicos, <bold>Cadernos de campo</bold>, v. 14/15, p. 319-338, 2006. DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.11606/issn.2316-9133.v15i14-15p319-338">10.11606/issn.2316-9133.v15i14-15p319-338</ext-link>.</p>
    <p>VIVEIROS DE CASTRO, Eduardo. <bold>Metafísicas caníbales. Líneas de antropología postestructural</bold>. Buenos Aires: Katz, 2010.</p>
    <p>VUOTO, Diego Luis. <bold>Aspectos de la interrelación entre la fauna y la cultura Toba-Taksek</bold>. Director: José Braunstein.1981. 130 f. Tesis (Licenciatura en Antropología). Facultad de Filosofía y Letras, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, 1981.</p>
    <p>WAGNER, Roy. <bold>The invention of culture</bold>. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1981[1975].</p>
    <p>WRIGHT, Pablo. <bold>Ser-en-el-Sueno. Crónicas de historia y vida toba</bold>. Buenos Aires: Biblos. 2008.</p>
  </body>
  <back/>
</article>
